<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Renovation Diary</title>
        <description>Joseph renovates his kitchen.</description>
        <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/</link>
        <atom:link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Sun, 04 Oct 2020 12:49:42 -0500</pubDate>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Oct 2020 12:49:42 -0500</lastBuildDate>
        <generator>Jekyll v4.0.1</generator>
        
            <item>
                <title>Finding an Architect</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve crossed the Rubicon. On Friday, I signed the paperwork to engage an architectural practice and get the project underway. I’ll have more to share about what I’m doing later once the actual design and build processes get underway. For now, I’ll walk through the mechanics of even finding an architect to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the beginning, I’ve wanted to hire an architect. But it wasn’t entirely clear whether my project was big enough to justify hiring one. Obviously if you’re building a house, you’ll need an architect. If the project is really small — replacing a bathroom vanity or installing built-in bookcases — you probably don’t need an architect. Others advised me that an architect would add to the project cost, and that a good design-build contractor could deal with my changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I found a credible contractor, though, it became clear I needed an architect in at least some capacity. Their stated reason had something to do with regulations governing fire suppression systems. There’s a fire sprinkler in my kitchen, and it’s possible it may need to be moved. That, apparently, requires a registered architect to sign off on the plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between my ambivalence about the contractor to begin with and the supposed requirement, when I decided to dust this project off around a month ago I decided I would at least explore the idea of hiring an architect. If they told me my project was too small, at least I’d know that I had made the right choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding an architect, though, proved to be harder than I would’ve guessed. Most of the obvious resources like Houzz were unhelpful in that the sort order of firms tended to correlate with the size or “prestige” of the practice, and there weren’t a lot of other levers to find what I was looking for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether it’s being in New England or being in the US more generally, most firms seem to cater to people who want something either very cookie cutter or very showy. There are lots of photos of double-wide Wolf ranges that cost more than some compact cars and other touches that look&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://st.hzcdn.com/simgs/pictures/kitchens/kitchen-krieger-associates-architects-inc-img~ad81ab970f7c97cc_9-4138-1-8234192.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;No thanks kitchen image&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;A cookie-cutter high-end suburban kitchen. At least this one looks well-executed, even if the design is a little tired. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.houzz.fr/photos/kitchen-phvw-vp~771539&quot;&gt;Photo&lt;/a&gt; courtesy &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.houzz.fr/hznb/professionnels/architecte/krieger-associates-architects-inc-pfvwus-pf~1702898409&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Krieger + Associates Architects, Inc.&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are places like Architizer or even Instagram. But the listing sites don’t tend to be comprehensive — the practice I hired isn’t on Architizer, for example — and Instagram is hard to browse if you’re looking for more than “inspiration.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, I found a firm through a combination of meticulousness and good luck. The initial shortlist of firms came from literally clicking on close to 100 firms’ listings on Houzz and though more straightforward Web searches. From there, a few never wrote back to my emails, and a few set up initial consultations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite what I would’ve guessed, a lot of firms have such a backlog of work that at least a few couldn’t have fit me in until the next year. Fortunately, the director of one practice was able to refer me to &lt;a href=&quot;https://bos-ua.com/about/&quot;&gt;BOS|UA&lt;/a&gt;, who (most importantly) really impressed me, and had enough capacity to start my small project immediately to boot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every practice I talked to made me feel pretty confident that hiring an architect was the right choice. Even the fanciest-looking practices that listed very big, very expensive projects on their websites seemed very down to earth and willing to take on my project. They all, even in my brief consultations, had ideas that never would have crossed my mind. The architects at the practice I wound up hiring suggested, for instance, that there were a few ways I might avoid moving my electrical panel. Avoiding that one change alone probably covers the cost of hiring them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of which, I have since discovered that architects’ fees typically run about 10-15% of the construction cost. In other words, for a $50,000 project, the architects’ fees would run round $5,000 to $7,500. Some will literally charge a fraction of the construction bill. Others — including all the firms that made my shortlist, which was not intentional but probably not a coincidence — bill either hourly or with fixed fees. As one person put it to me, there really isn’t a lot more work involved for the architects if I happen to want a really expensive refrigerator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the initial consultation, the architects sent over a formal proposal. Basically, a contract about the work, including a rough schedule, pricing, and each side’s obligations. Signing that document on Friday is what kicked off this whole process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All-in, I’ll be spending about $4500 in architects’ fees, which works out to something like 15% of my (very provisional) $30,000 construction budget. There’s some variability in the cost of the construction administration phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fee structure breaks down roughly equally through the different major design phases. The first chunk to establish the current site conditions, the second to build a rough schematic design, the third to develop more detailed drawings for regulatory approval, and fourth the final detailed drawings and final budget tweaks. That comes to about $4,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there, I’ve chosen to spend the extra money — billed hourly — to have the architects manage the team of contractors actually doing the construction. On the surface it seems like a slightly absurd level of bureaucracy for such a small project: I manage the architects who manage the general contractor who manages the actual workers. But even my brief interactions with general contractors have convinced me this will probably be worth the money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll have more to say on the project design in a few weeks. They’re working away: my first design meeting happens at the end of the month. For now, I’ve been asked to put together a mood board (the headline image) to give the architects an idea of what I want. I’m also beginning to think about cash flow, the true limits of what I’m going to spend, and how I’m going to cope for a few months without a kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I have a chance, I may share some preliminary thoughts about those questions. For now, stay tuned.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 04 Oct 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/finding-an-architect</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/finding-an-architect</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Where We've Been</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Before I get into the details of what’s happening with the kitchen project now, I thought it would be a good idea to take a step back and explore how I got here. It’s been a long journey from deciding to take on this project to realizing it’s harder than I thought, and then having plans derailed by a once-in-a-lifetime public health crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was shopping for a place to buy, it quickly became clear that the kitchens fell into one of two camps. Either they hadn’t been touched for 30 years, or they were recently renovated, but with questionable taste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;images/shopping.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Questionable kitchen&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;One option I didn’t go for. The cabinet installers were so bad, I can tell some of the doors aren’t in alignment by looking at this photo, which is hiding many smaller sins. This apartment also had the disadvantage of being in a basement.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One apartment I looked at (sadly, I forgot to take a photo) had a kitchen that was more or less a corner of the living room in which they’d installed a $10,000 Sub-Zero refrigerator and a half-size dishwasher. Yes, I could have removed it after purchase, but then I’ve have had to pay for a $10,000 refrigerator that I didn’t want. Others, like the one in the photo above, were clearly designed to tick boxes on a real estate listing, not work well as a system. One easy check: nothing I looked at had a dishwasher that cost more than my most expensive stock pot. Admittedly, my most expensive stock pot cost about $400 — which is a lot for a piece of cookware — but it’s also really not that much for a dishwasher. By comparison, that expanse of low-grade jet black granite probably cost upwards of $5,000. It truly boggles my mind someone would want such fancy worktops but skimp on way more useful choices, like spending the extra money to get drawers with nice runners instead of shelves in the lower cabinets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;images/shopping2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Questionable kitchen&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Another option I didn’t take. The second “bedroom” was more of a closet. Note that they did upgrade to (ugly) beige granite worktops to tick the “granite counter” box on real estate listings.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I chose to go for something that hadn’t been touched for 30 years. How hard could it be to scape together $20,000 to renovate a kitchen? As it turns out, pretty hard when you vastly underestimate all the leeches who siphon money off unsuspecting people when you buy a home and encounter some novel personal financial issues. (I’m not allowed to discuss those for legal reasons.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;images/current.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Kitchen&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A glimpse into my current tiny kitchen, taken the day I moved in.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time I had the money put together last fall, I also realized that $20,000 wasn’t going to be enough for my tiny kitchen and big ambitions. At the moment, I’m budgeting closer to $30,000, and I wouldn’t be surprised if I spend more like $40,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;images/sketch.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sketch&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The current layout.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this was a small project, the idea of hiring an architect seemed like an indulgence at first. I felt good enough planning something out with basic CAD software to hand off to what I hoped would be a competent contractor who might be capable of helping me iron out some of the more ambiguous details. My choices were fairly modest: Ikea cabinets to save money, locating services like plumbing to avoid expensive changes to the structure. Even that, however, proved to be too much. Every contractor I spoke to said I’d need an architect, if only to comply build local building regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;images/sketch2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sketch&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The renovation concept.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of, the process of finding a contractor isn’t one known for being pleasant. My experience didn’t do much to counter that. No one seems to have realized it’s easy to set up an email address, let alone a website. Hunting them down was a game of telephone tag. Call at off hours, and they’ve checked out for the day. Call during the day, and they barely give you notice because they’re trying to finish their work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I did find someone, it was not an especially productive relationship. Despite being a man, I’m pretty sure I fell victim to “mansplaining.” Because my kitchen was built in the 1950s, they decided to put the electrical panel in the kitchen. Rotating the layout virtually necessitates moving that, which is expensive, probably in the region of $3000. It’s a strange feeling to put that in an email and mention it on the phone up front, only to have the someone call and spend 20 minutes explaining it again, as if there was no way I could have understood it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, of course, the pandemic hit. With it came a construction ban in my building and the necessity that I work from home more or less indefinitely. The idea of living off microwave meals and takeout isn’t super appealing to me. But at least in the pre-covid world I would have been able to commandeer friends’ kitchens, eat out at restaurants, and travel freely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was the realization that the public health crisis may last for another year or more that pushed me to bring this project back to life. If I wait for the situation to really improve, it might be 2022 before I have a new kitchen — five years after I moved in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next time, I’ll share my experiences finding an architect to whip the project into shape. I figure, if I have to engage a firm anyway, I might as well have them help me build something that goes beyond my amateur efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/where-weve-been</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/where-weve-been</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Resurrection</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been almost three years since I bought my apartment with the idea of renovating the kitchen, and I still haven’t done anything beyond install a new dishwasher. The first hurdle was getting the money together. Even my tiny kitchen with modest upgrades is going to be fairy expensive. Then, of course, the world was hit with a pandemic. Stuck at home and without the ability to really travel or visit friends, I didn’t love the idea of living on a construction site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I realized we could be in this situation for a very long time, however. It’s time to take the leap and begin the renovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve set up this new blog to keep a running diary of the process. I’m hoping to keep interested people informed with a difference. Yes, I’ll have the usual photos and commentary of the process as it goes along. But I’m also going to be very honest about details that a lot of people seem to skim over. Living on a construction site isn’t fun, and major home renovations are not cheap. It’s misleading to imagine that you can achieve Architectural Digest-quality with pluck and elbow grease. I’ll spend more on my architects than you’d pay for a high-end watch or fancy handbag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m hoping that by chronicling all the little details most people omit, this will be a more interesting and a more useful guide for anyone else hoping to take on a project like mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my next post, I’ll piece together more of a project update recapping where I am today, and what’s happening as I dust off the project and get it moving again. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/resurrection</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/resurrection</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>