<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Renovation Diary</title>
        <description>Joseph renovates his kitchen.</description>
        <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/</link>
        <atom:link href="https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jul 2022 10:39:10 -0500</pubDate>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Jul 2022 10:39:10 -0500</lastBuildDate>
        <generator>Jekyll v4.0.1</generator>
        
            <item>
                <title>Inspected</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;There’s not too much to say for the last few weeks. But there was a bit of progress: earlier in the week the electrical inspector paid the site a visit, and passed the work. The project is still behind schedule, but this is encouraging progress to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a budget perspective, there were a few interesting twists. The plumbing work to move the sink and add laundry wound up being more expensive than the original scope of the project suggested. The plumber hadn’t anticipated needing to replace quite as much of the drain and vent stack from what I’m told.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the plus side, through some accounting I don’t totally understand, the very expensive extra plumbing work got offset with savings elsewhere, so only wound up costing about $1,000 more net.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking ahead, passing the rough inspections is a big step because it makes closing the walls (i.e., putting up the wallboard) possible. It goes without saying, that’s an important step in making progress.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jul 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/inspected</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/inspected</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Electric Progress</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;While I can’t quite tell if it’s done-done, there’s been encouraging progress on the electrical wiring. Most of the circuits are in place, and they’ve wired up my new panel to the original feeder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting to see all the circuits run. We think of electricity as being an almost magical force, but in reality there really is a run of metal wire all the way from the outlet to a power station somewhere many miles away. There’s so much wiring!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until the walls are closed and the outlets and switches are installed, they can’t wire up all the new circuits to the new panel. But, since I’m still living on site, they did make sure that the circuits in the living spaces have power, which resulted in the rather hilarious situation I’m in now with a single 15 amp breaker in the panel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/electric-rough-solitary.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Electrical panel&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;A solitary breaker&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the work is more straightforward. There’s a tangle of circuits by the sink for the garbage disposal, dishwasher, and the transformers required for the LED strip lights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/electric-rough-sink.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wiring near the sink&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;A tangle of circuits&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The circuits for the oven and cooktop are impressive to look at. Both appliances require more power — the cooktop I’ve selected can drive 7,700 W into a single pan! — which means they need an additional wire to get 240 V. They’re also much more substantial wires so they can safely run at 30 or 40 amps when they’re running at full power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/electric-rough-big.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wiring for the cooktop and oven&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;More substantial wiring for power-hungry cooking appliances&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not entirely sure what happens next. The inspection certificate on my front door suggests the electrical inspection hasn’t happened yet, and there are a couple of changes that need to happen on the electrical work so far. One outlet is in the wrong place. I’d also like to see if it’s possible to have a run of unconnected wiring left in the walls for a future bathroom renovation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/electric-progress</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/electric-progress</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Plumbing Progress</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Progress continues working toward completion of the first fix plumbing and electric. The plumber was on site several days running the new drain, water, and vent lines for the relocated kitchen sink. From what I can tell, everything is ready to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s kind of fun to see the parts of the old drain and vent stack that the plumber cut out to tie the new lines in. They’re very substantial chunks of pipe. Slightly more terrifying to peer into the old sections of pipe and see the accretion of sludge or corrosion or whatever builds up inside drain lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/plumbing-old-drain.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sections of pipe&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Drain and vent lines removed to make way for new adapters&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My building is about to spend $1.5 million replacing all the exterior balcony railings and floors. Perhaps the drain lines only need a good clean. I do slightly wonder how much it will cost and how complicated it will be if the drains actually need to be replaced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My inner software developer brain wonders why the building doesn’t require anyone who opens the wall to replace that section of drain and vent completely, or even subsidize that. Compared to the complication of opening and then reassembling the wall of everyone’s apartments in the future, the expense and minor complication of replacing the whole section seems negligible. Perhaps another casualty of the American delusion we can all be completely self-sufficient. Or our procedure fetish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I’m still waiting for the electrical question to be resolved, keeping my fingers crossed that they’ll let me get away with not having to run a new feeder wire. From what I understand, getting the electrical work done is the next big step.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/plumbing-progress</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/plumbing-progress</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Inching to the First Fix</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been an interesting few weeks. I spent over two of them elsewhere, mostly because I was afraid that as they got going on the more involved electrical and plumbing work, I might not have power or water. In the end, that didn’t happen, but it was still nice to escape the construction site and take a few days off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I was gone, a the project did make some progress. They removed asbestos, did more wiring, and (today) got going on the plumbing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the asbestos removal, they tore down what remained of the old kitchen wall, and then added new framing where that had been. From what I could tell, that was a relatively straightforward process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More involved (and still unresolved) was the electrical work. The most straightforward reading of the electrical code meant that I was initially required to upgrade my 60 A service — a relic from the 1950s — with 100 A service, the modern minimum. That requires upgrading the conductors that run from my apartment to the electric meter, no mean feat when that new feeder line had to run through a 70-year-old conduit buried in cast concrete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite several attempts, the electricians were unable to run the new feeder. The current plan is to go back to the city electrical department and argue that the actual load fits within the limits of 60 A service. It’s not a huge apartment after all. Whether that will land remains to be seen. I’m hoping it will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what I understand, the alternative would be incredibly expensive and disruptive: destroying the common hallway to run a new feeder through the ceiling there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/rough-panel.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Electrical panel&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The panel upgrade begins&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, more (successful) electrical wiring happened. Several new circuits were run, and they began the process of upgrading my panel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regulations dominated aesthetic considerations in one case. They had to add an outlet for the small run of counter space to the left of the new sink. The electrical code requires any run of counter space over 12” to have at least one outlet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/rough-kitchen-outlet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;An outlet&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The wall paneling will have to be marred by an outlet&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More interestingly, they were able to wire for the LED strips using very narrow 18 gauge conductors, as (presumably) the LEDs are so low power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/rough-18.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;18 gauge&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Wiring for the LED strips&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work on the first fix plumbing also got started. There’s not a ton to see yet, only the beginnings of new drain and vent lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/sink-rough-drain.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;18 gauge&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;A drain for the new kitchen sink&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress, for sure. I’m less sure they’re going to make it to the early July deadline.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/inching-to-first-fix</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/inching-to-first-fix</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>The Pause</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Our strange economic moment strikes again. All other considerations aside, the biggest snag from the asbestos discovery has been time. In particular, a two week wait for the remediation firm to have a slot in their schedule to fit me in. So, I wait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s particularly maddening because this more or less has to happen before anything else can go on. From what I understand, the next steps are finishing the first fix plumbing and electric. The plumbing is literally blocked by the asbestos: it’s on the hot water lines. The electrical work is blocked by the incomplete demolition (blocked by the asbestos), and probably the workplace safety issues posed by discovering asbestos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what the firm said, they’ll be able to do the removal in a couple of weeks on the 6th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s nothing I can do about it, and certainly the asbestos should be removed. That doesn’t completely make up for the annoyance of another two weeks of living in the earliest stage of construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those interested in details, it’s going to run about $1,800 for the remediation work, plus $135 for the permit. Completion also requires that I engage an independent consultant to verify the environment is safe, another $350 to $500.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/the-pause</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/the-pause</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>The Hiccups</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with some good news. Since the last post, the flooring from &lt;a href=&quot;http://pidfloors.com&quot;&gt;PID&lt;/a&gt; arrived on site, as did the new ventilation hood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new hood is exciting for very mundane reasons. Namely, it’s really hard to get appliances right now. While there’s still quite a few to go — my oven probably won’t be here until August — progress is progress, and should be appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flooring is more of a relief. It was only ever possible for me to see photos of finished floors and a couple of small samples. That I still liked the choice when I plucked out a few full planks to look at was reassuring. I can’t wait to see it all installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/floor-plank.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The new flooring, up closer&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Real wood flooring to replace the Pergo&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now to the bad news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living in a well-established historical neighborhood has its benefits. Mature trees. Nice architecture. Streets designed for people, not cars. Unfortunately it also means old buildings with old building quirks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case, that turned out to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asbestos&quot;&gt;asbestos&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/asbestos.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Asbestos&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;If you've ever wondered what asbestos looks like, it's this&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a great insulator and fire retardant. It’s also a serious danger to human health, and has to be very delicately removed when it’s found. In my case, that’s around the main hot water line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From talking to the remediation company, the pipe insulation in my plumbing stack isn’t that big of a deal. They said it could probably be removed and certified in a single day. But it’s not going to be cheap. Among other things, I have to pay $350 just for the independent verification and certification after the material has been removed. People will be wearing serious respirators. Plastic wall barriers will be set up. And industrial-grade HEPA filters will be running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel like I really lucked out that I happen to have domestic-scale HEPA filters running as a matter of course and I have a vacuum cleaner with a HEPA filter I’ve been using to do extra cleanup. At least some asbestos has been disturbed as part of the work so far; it’s nice to know I’ve been protected. A very bare silver lining of the pandemic. I decided to buy them to assuage my guilt in having (a very small and select number of) people over during the height of pandemic in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other forces conspired to throw a wrench in one of the parts of my project I had been most excited about. It looks like I can’t have my in-unit laundry after all. Perhaps I should get a Costco membership and start buying breakfast cereal in bulk. I’m going to have a lot more closet space than I had anticipated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My contractor still hasn’t been able to provide a full schedule, so it’s hard to say exactly what comes next. Probably asbestos remediation, if I had to guess. That may also take care of the remaining demolition that needed to happen before the final framing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the framing is done and the asbestos is gone, my guess is that they’ll move to finish first fix plumbing and electric, including the high-stakes feeder wire replacement project.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/hiccups</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/hiccups</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>An Electric Saga</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;There was some excitement on site yesterday. I didn’t stay all day, but I managed to catch several people first thing in the morning. That provided me with a few updates, and I got to see the electrician’s crew in action as they began the first fix wiring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/ff-wide.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wide angle of the progress&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, the tangible progress is the most satisfying. They ran the rough wiring for a few of the smaller circuits, for appliances like the fridge-freezer and the dishwasher, and the various new outlets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/ff-old-switch.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A pointless old switch finally going away&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;A pointless lamp switch being removed, to my great pleasure&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They removed a lot of the vestigial outlets and wiring too, such as the old runs for the countertop outlets in the kitchen. Sadly, one of the few ceiling lights had to go. There was no way to save it without aesthetic compromises I wasn’t willing to live with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/ff-old-light.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;An old light&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;A sadder loss: it wasn't possible to save this ceiling light without other ugly aesthetic compromises&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s still no exact plan for the vexed question of the electrical panel’s feeder wire. The electrician was able to get the city to approve a three-wire configuration, using the conduit as the ground. But running a new feeder 100 feet through a 70-year-old conduit buried in a concrete slab is not sure thing. There’s thus some planning involved in the step: the electrician wants to have a “plan B” ready to go. Namely, destroying the common hallway to run a new feeder that way. I have to get the condo association to sign off on that before that’s on the table as the fallback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/ff-checklist.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Electrician's checklist&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the plus side, I finally got everyone to understand the nuanced situation with the Miele heat pump dryer I’ve specified. This may save the day, depending on the electrician’s calculations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/ff-two-gang.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Two-gang box&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it uses a heat pump, this dryer consumes substantially less power than a traditional electric tumble dryer, and so requires only a 120 V 20 amp circuit rather than a 240 V 30 amp “dryer” circuit. It’s possible this gets the load down to below 60 amps, and no new feeder wire at all is required. Which would be great, for many reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, as the electrical situation somewhat stabilizes, the plumbing has introduced a new wrinkle of its own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that he’s looked more carefully at the situation, the plumber has decided it’s not possible to use the kitchen’s drain line for the laundry stack. The exact logic isn’t entirely clear to me. The architects are consulting with an engineer to try and work around the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on the outcome of that consultation, this wrinkle opens the possibility they have to run the plumbing through my bathroom stack. Which would mean opening more walls and tearing apart my bathroom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once my finances have recovered from the kitchen project, I would eventually like to redo the bathroom. If they need to do a slightly ugly repair after tearing the wall open, maybe that’s fine, especially if it gets a sort of head start on the demolition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been told they’ll have an opinion by later this week. Perhaps I’ll be looking at tile now after all.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/electrical</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/electrical</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Framing, Part III</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;The crew made another trip and, as far as I can tell, they got the framing right on the third pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what I can tell, they simply picked the framing up, moved it forward, and reattached it to the ground. That also required extending the platform where the cabinets will sit, and adjust the box for the soffit over the refrigerator and laundry cabinets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything is now in the same plane, and the new spaces have been properly delineated. While this apartment is never going to be enormous, I’m pleasantly surprised at the amount of space in the former kitchen area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the framing looks a little rough. It’s not clear to me whether that’s normal and reasonable, or something I should be worried about. I’m never going to see the framing once the project is done. Presumably framing with more finesse would be slower and more expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also removed more of the wall of the former kitchen space, per what I think were the plumber’s instructions. It’s interesting to see the guts of the building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/plumbing-wall.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;More wall is removed&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here too I’m slightly confused: the updating framing drawings suggested the whole wall would come down and be replaced with a new 2x4 wall. Avoiding work is good for me, the contractor, and the planet. I worry that not following the plan will cause other problems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/framing-iii</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/framing-iii</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Framing, Part II</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;The rest of the week saw a bit of activity. It’s felt a bit like one step forward, two steps back. The framing is closer, but still not quite there. The plumbing work got going. And the electrical panel issue continues to vex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/framing-view.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;View out the new aperture&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The new view out from the former kitchen area, correctly framed&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the framing front, the team came back for a second pass. They got closer; clearly the new set of drawings helped. Unfortunately, it’s still not quite right. The framing now has the aperture designed to let light into the former kitchen space, behind the new kitchen sink and dishwasher. It’s also been trimmed down to the right height, about a foot off the ceiling — it’s designed to line up with the height of structural concrete beams running through the space — that should let in even more light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/XhTnkUX7Fgs&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they didn’t quite get it right. The whole wall needs to be in one plane, not offset. Talking to both the architects and the project manager on the job, it will get fixed. In all honesty, I do find it rather baffling. I noticed the issue myself, and I’m definitely not an expert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/framing-alignment-close.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Out of plane&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The whole wall should be in the same plane&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the plumber stopped by to begin getting ready for the first fix. From what I can tell, he removed the old plumbing and added valves off the building’s main water lines in preparation for the next step. I’m guessing that can’t happen until the framing gets fixed, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/discarded-plumbing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Remnants of plumbing&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The old sink connections&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/plumbing-capped.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Capped plumbing&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;New valves in the kitchen plumbing stack&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The electrical situation continues to cause a problem. Apparently the head electrician is on vacation in Brazil, and so isn’t around to negotiate with the electrical inspectors. It would really be nice if I didn’t need to run a new feeder through the common corridor, if they insist that I have a four-wire feeder that won’t fit in the conduit.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/framing-ii</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/framing-ii</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Shopping and Delivery</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;No building as such has happened in the last few days, but that doesn’t mean there’s nothing happening. There’s been some coordination on the framing, I’m working on procuring the fixtures I’m responsible for, and the cabinets have arrived on site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the framing, my architects prepared some new and hopefully clearer drawings for the framers on their next visit. Without putting too fine a point on it, it’s pretty clear that the framing isn’t what it needed to be. Having chatted with everyone about the issue, I have some confidence that the framing will get resolved in due course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I’m working on the procurement of parts I have to buy: the appliances, plumbing fixtures, and electrical components like lighting. The sink and faucet arrived almost as soon as I ordered them, thankfully in the right colors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/sink-box.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sink in a box&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The sink and faucet have arrived&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest is proving a bit trickier. The vent hood was supposed to ship this week, and still hasn’t. The remaining appliances that I’m ordering from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yaleappliance.com&quot;&gt;local Miele dealer&lt;/a&gt; are more concerning still in our pandemic supply chain era. The refrigerator-freezer is only a few weeks out, which is good. All the Miele appliances, though, from the oven to the tumble dryer, are at least a month out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re having me put down a 50% deposit to get them on order, and then I have to cross my fingers they’ll get here in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More excitingly, the cabinets have made it to site. The delivery process was not quite as smooth as it could’ve been. They didn’t give us any notice: it was a good thing I was up early on the day they arrived. More outside my control, the largest of the panels didn’t fit in the freight elevator. I’m having to temporarily store those in the common basement area. Apparently they need to go to someone’s shop for further processing in any case, so I’m hoping they won’t linger in the basement long enough for anyone to get upset with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/reform-panels-packaging.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Reform panels&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Some of the larger cabinet doors and panels&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/reform-packaging.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cabinet doors in packaging&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;A few panels in their protective packing&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/reform-date.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Reform packing slip&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;They really did start working on this order over a year ago&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the electrical front, more drama still. From what I’ve been told, the electrical inspector has now decided that in addition to upgrading to minimum 100 amp service, I also need to run a feeder line with four conductors: the two hots, neutral, and ground. This poses a problem because the existing conduit, which runs through a cast concrete slab to the electrical meter in the trash room, is only sized for three conductors. Complying with that would require ripping apart the ceiling in the common hallway, which no one is going to enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/old-panel-uncovered.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The existing panel&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The existing panel with its cover off: the feeder is the thick set of conductors coming into the box on the top right&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m hoping they can get an exemption to this, or better still convince the inspector to let me keep the existing feeder wire in place. It’s been fine for over a dozen other people who’ve done recent renovations. Why they would suddenly require it now is unclear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/plumbing-wall-wide.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wall with plumbing&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/plumbing-wall-detail.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wall with plumbing, detail&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plumber stopped by last week as well. He wants the lower half of the wall against the plumbing stack removed to do the new work. And there’s consensus that the supports for that wall are unlikely to be sufficient for all the weight that it will support. (This makes me slightly concerned that I had several upper cabinets filled with dishes hanging off of it!) So: the wall is coming down in the second and hopefully final batch of demolition slated to happen in the next few days.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 17 Apr 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/shopping</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/shopping</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>