<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Renovation Diary</title>
        <description>Joseph renovates his kitchen.</description>
        <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/</link>
        <atom:link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Sun, 27 Feb 2022 10:42:13 -0600</pubDate>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Feb 2022 10:42:13 -0600</lastBuildDate>
        <generator>Jekyll v4.0.1</generator>
        
            <item>
                <title>Bidding, Part III</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m almost at the end of the bidding process. It hasn’t exactly ended the way I’d hoped, but then the last two years have changed my expectations pretty considerably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contract still isn’t quite ready to sign, but I’m very close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one big outstanding question has been resolved: I’m going to have to replace the feeder wire to my electrical panel at a cost of around $5,000. Reading between the lines, the city wasn’t able to grandfather me in with 75 amp service. It’s unfortunate from a cost perspective, though on the other hand, gives me lots of headroom for my menagerie of electrical appliances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My architects have also consulted with the prospective contractor to trim out any unnecessary expenses. It hasn’t amounted to much relative to the total bill. They’ve cut out expenses like a few hundred dollars to run a water line to my fridge-freezer, which doesn’t need one, as it doesn’t have an ice maker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, I think this goes to show the value of having experts combing through the details. The small amount of time spent scrutinizing the plans has saved far more than the cost of those professional services. Of course, I’m very aware that hiring an architect (or, let’s be honest, my aesthetic aspirations) probably increased the cost of the project in making it less straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next week I’ll coordinate scheduling and dates. My architects have also said they’ll draw up a standard AIA (American Institute of Architects) owner-contractor agreement, rather than the document provided by my prospective contractor. I’ll probably have more to say about that once I’ve seen it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it stands now, the quote breaks down like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Item&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Cost&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Permitting&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$810&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;General conditions&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$7,400&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Preparation and demolition&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$3,600&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Carpentry (including flooring material)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$17,300&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Electrical&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$14,800&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Plumbing&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$7,800&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Patching and painting&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$4,300&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Countertops&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$11,900&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding that up (and rounding slightly) brings the whole cost of the kitchen construction and materials to a cool $67,900. Adding the kitchen would pull that up another $22,400 in the itemized bid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nor is that going to be the total cost. I’ve already spent almost $17,000 on the cabinets and professional fees. (Though some of that is pre-paying for construction administration.) And I’ll need to add another $11,000 for appliances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That will bring this whole project in at close to $90,000. A staggering sum of money, if I’m honest. And almost exactly double the original budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be back next week with more on the actual execution, scheduling, and taking the plunge.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2022 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/bid-iii</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/bid-iii</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Feeder Wire</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m very close to signing a contract to get the program going. The last detail: pinning down the cost of the electrical work. In particular, the core upgrades necessary for the increased load that the renovation will put on the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went into the project knowing that I’d need to upgrade the panel. For starters, I’m adding enough new circuits I need a new panel simply for space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Current code requires more loads go on separate circuits for safety. More importantly, I’m adding a bunch of new appliances: a separate oven and cooktop (rather than the existing all-in-one range), each of which need a double-gang slot to carry 240 V to those appliances; and then a washer and dryer. Fortunately, the Miele heat pump dryer that I’ve specified only requires a 15 amp circuit, but each laundry appliance does need to go on its own separate circuit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relatively straightforward panel replacement had already been factored into the bid. But there was an additional twist that needed additional following up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these new appliances also require more overall capacity on the panel. My current service to the apartment is only 60 amps, common when my building was built in the 1950s, but well below current standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the electrician, the existing feeder wire — the wire that runs from the electric meter to my apartment — can only safely carry 75 amps. That’s enough to support all the new electrical load I’m putting on the system, but below the 100 amp minimum that code currently requires for a dwelling of any size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question then is whether it will be possible to have my system grandfathered in. If it can be, that’s a huge savings: there’s no additional work to do. If it can’t, then the electrician will need to run a new feeder wire from my apartment to the meter. I haven’t seen pricing, but there’s no way that’s going to be inexpensive. The meter is about 100 feet down the common corridor from my apartment, and the new wire won’t run in a completely straight line. Moreover, it will have to run through a conduit buried in a cast concrete slab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it has to happen, I don’t have much choice but to pay for it. I also don’t envy the person who has to do the work.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 12 Feb 2022 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/feeder-wire</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/feeder-wire</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Bidding, Part II</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Almost six months ago, I accepted my fate: this project is going to cost a lot more than I had hoped and anticipated. On the plus side, I’ve been waiting so long, I’m in a position to do that somewhat comfortably. But that doesn’t remove the feeling that everything is just that little bit out of reach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After getting a bid roughly double the original labor and materials estimate, I figured it would at least be worth exploring what it would cost to do “everything,” meaning mostly adding a gut remodel of the apartment’s bathroom to my project scope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the week, the contractor visited again to finalize pricing on that, and I think it’s pushed me to make some decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the good news: my contractor is ready to go. It’s likely the kitchen portion of my project will get going next month, in March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bad news: it’s still very expensive. The latest bid for both my kitchen renovation and the gut remodel of the bathroom comes to a cool $81,000 or so. I think it’s important to share that number. There’s something deeply frustrating about seeing all these renovation projects on TV or on blogs, and the authors making it seem like pluck and effort are the reason you don’t live in an Instagram-ready home. This stuff is expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That $81,000 isn’t the totality of the project’s cost either. I’ve already spent around $10,000 on cabinets (still hanging out in a warehouse somewhere in New Jersey), and doing the kitchen and bathroom would require about $10,000 worth of appliances, another $5,000 for bathroom fixtures, and then some amount for me to relocate while my apartment is being ripped apart. Add that up and the total cost comes to around $100,000. Put differently: more than I’d like to spend right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plus: there are a few more smaller tweaks I’d like to make — adding wardrobe space in the bedroom, replacing some very bland millwork in the living space — that would add even more to that number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s still some finalization to be done, but for anyone interested, the contract as currently specified looks something like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$810 for permitting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$3,100 for project management&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$4,300 for site preparation and demolition&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$20,000 for carpentry&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$11,300 for electrical&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$15,800 for plumbing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$2,700 for drywall work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$3,400 for painting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$20,500 for tile and counters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having never done this before, I was also interested to understand much more specifically when and how the cost is spread over the duration of the contract. If you’re curious too, the breakdown looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Around 10% at contract signature&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Around 25% when work begins&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Around 20% when framing plus rough-in (first fix) plumbing and electric is completed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Around 15% after the cabinets and tile are in&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Around 15% after flooring and second fix plumbing and electric is completed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Around 15% after final inspections and completion of work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I can’t really swing dropping $100,000 right now, the thought is to break the project into two phases: do the kitchen now, and then do the bathroom maybe a year from now after my finances have had a chance to recover. Based on the earlier bid, I’m hoping that I can get the kitchen-only portion down to around $55,000, putting me somewhere like $65,000 including the appliances I’ll buy myself. It’s a lot of money, but I’m in the fortunate position that I can spend that pretty comfortably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should have an update next week on exactly what comes of that. I’m a little nervous, to be sure. Home renovations are notorious for being stressful, complicated, and running over budget. But after the very unpleasant experience buying my apartment — which really was at the absolute limits of what I could afford at the time — I’m very happy choosing the slightly more conservative path. Spending $65,000 is a pretty dizzying concept. But I also have the money, and enough beyond that set aside for a pretty catastrophic worst-case scenario.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/bid-ii</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/bid-ii</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>At a Crossroads</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;The pandemic has thrown a wrench in just about every part of this project. Getting information from the potential cabinet companies took forever. It took forever to order the cabinets. It took forever to get the cabinets delivered and shipped. It took forever to even get me flooring samples when we got to that stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then it took forever to find a contractor. The last six months, more or less, and not for lack of trying. The results of that process have thrown a wrench in the project. Either way, it’s going to be a lot more expensive than I had hoped. Thanks, pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, a few steps back. A few years ago, when I bought this apartment, I had poorly-informed delusions about how much such a project might cost. In retrospect, the thought I could do anything meaningful for $25,000 was laughable. After a few years of savings and a bit of re-calibration, I landed on a more realistic figure of $45,000 for the project when I brought it back to life a year ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/siematic-pure-010.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;SieMatic Pure&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;A SieMatic Kitchen I can't afford. (Image credit: SieMatic)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working to that figure has been a strong input to the process. It’s the reason I bought cabinets from Reform rather than, say, SieMatic as I’d hoped might just maybe be affordable. (If you haven’t read &lt;a href=&quot;cabients-part-ii&quot;&gt;that post&lt;/a&gt;, they very much were not even remotely within my budget.) It was equally reassuring that my architects had done a project along the same lines in 2019 that had construction costs in line with that sort of budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the pandemic threw a wrench in all that. Accounting for the cabinets and appliances, that left around $25,000 for construction and materials. Not a trivial sum! The bids my architects got blew that out of the water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first was for roughly $44,000. The second was for close to $50,000, nearly double the budgeted amount. The third wouldn’t even give a precise estimate, from what I heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it was conveyed to me, several pieces contributed to these astronomical quotes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, supply chain issues. In the design my architects put together, the worktops and backsplash are designed to be made out of Corian. The counters need to be in half-inch because they need to support the work of cooking. But the backsplash and protective caps on the upper cabinets don’t, and could be made of (much cheaper) quarter-inch Corian. The quarter-inch product, however, is apparently not easy to get right now, so one of the bids used half-inch instead, doubling the materials cost for that component.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, the incredible demand that still exists for contractors and people in the construction industry. It’s likely some of the prices are so high simply to make the market clear. If you want to do a project now, it will not be cheap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, my impression is that we slightly underestimated the overheads involved in working in my neighborhood. Parking is scarce, and it’s a multi-family building (with all the concomitant rules and regulations), not a single-family suburban home with easy access and few restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What to do, then?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Either way, I’m resigned to spending more than I had planned to. Fortunately, I’m in a position to do that, so it shouldn’t be a big problem. The more vexed question is exactly how much more to spend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://st.hzcdn.com/simgs/pictures/salles-de-bain/abbeville-terre-grise-img~97715fc70daf124b_14-5849-1-7529adc.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A bathroom&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Sadly, I don't have this much space. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.houzz.fr/photos/abbeville-phvw-vp~150420990&quot;&gt;Photo&lt;/a&gt; courtesy &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.houzz.fr/pro/webuser-574038528/terre-grise&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Terre Grise&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current thought is to wait, hoping the demand for contractors cools down a bit, and expand the scope to spread out the project overheads a bit more. I had planned to eventually redo the bathroom and add more storage eventually, why not do it now? Especially if I have to spend so much more anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m still waiting on meta-estimates from the contractors on demand trends heading into next year. If they see it tapering off, that might be one indication to wait. And then, if I wind up doing the additional projects, it’s back to the drawing board with my architects to design a bathroom!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I’m going to have to start spending about $100 every month to keep my cabinets — which have made it to the US from Denmark — in storage somewhere in New Jersey.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 04 Sep 2021 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/crossroads</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/crossroads</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Before the Bids</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;More developments are afoot! The cabinet order is in, as mentioned last time. Next up, I’m making some final decisions about small details, like where to put outlets and light switches. I’ve also got to pick out the flooring that will replace the suspect plastic wood simulacrum that came with the apartment. With construction documents nearly done, it’s also time to send the bid out to potential contractors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The preliminary construction documents are very reassuring. Mostly in that they’re so detailed. I feel even better about having paid serious professionals to work up a detailed plan. It’s a easier to imagine the very expensive construction phase going well with less left to figure out in the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/preliminary-drawing.png&quot; alt=&quot;A preliminary drawing&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Part of the preliminary construction documents. The architects have drawn up detailed plans to confirm details and give the contractors a very precise idea what needs to be done. (Image credit: BOS|UA)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still need to do a bit more thinking. First, I need to confirm switch placement. Based on the plans, I don’t think I’ll have much to say. Rather cleverly — though apparently this is not unusual — the switch for the garbage disposal will be placed under the sink inside the cabinet rather than disrupt the harmony of the wall behind. I’m hoping it will be possible to add in a few more outlets here and there. They’re not the most attractive part of a space, but you can never have enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, I need to pick out the flooring. This has turned into a bit of an ordeal. Before I spend $5,000 on it, I figured it would be nice to see more than a little 4 by 4 inch sample. So I took a day off to go visit some flooring showrooms at the local design center. These fancy suppliers cater mostly to professionals, and so the showrooms are only open on weekdays during business hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/picture-frame.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A preliminary drawing&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Carlisle 'Picture Frame' flooring at the Boston Design Center showroom. This was one option suggested to me, the thought being another white European oak would go well with the cabinets also made of that material.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should’ve done more confirming before cycling over there to look around. I did manage to see one of the two flooring showrooms. Unfortunately, it was not the one that had my architects’ first pick. The other showroom was closed because, as it turned out, the person who runs the Boston one was out sick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/oven-in-the-wild.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My oven-to-be&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;While I was waiting, I nosed around a few of the kitchen showrooms. One display kitchen had the Miele 60cm oven I plan to buy installed.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, the preliminary construction drawings should make it possible to begin getting bids from contractors and thus start setting dates for when the actual work begins. I’m hoping the next post will have more to say about that. Or I’ll finally get the last of the flooring samples and have a final decision on that.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Thu, 04 Mar 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/about-to-bid</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/about-to-bid</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Cabinets, Part V</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Finally, the cabinets are ordered. But the pandemic strikes again: the final delivery window is 14 to 18 weeks. I’m hoping it will be possible to get the work started sooner. There’s a lot of demolition and construction that needs to happen before the cabinets go in. Then again, from what I hear, it may also be difficult to book a contractor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of the cabinet order itself, once it was ready to go, the process was pretty painless. The total bill came to $11,509. That doesn’t include all the cabinet boxes: the laundry, refrigerator, and upper cabinet boxes will be custom. But it does include additional paneling for the new entry-office area that will be created in the current kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/pegboard-final.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A refined version of the former kitchen area. The panels being ordered from Reform will make up the pegboard system. (Image credit: BOS|UA )&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next week or two I really will go look at flooring, and start figuring out how to get all my appliances here on time.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/cabinets-part-v</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/cabinets-part-v</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Cabinets, Part IV</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Getting a final specification for the cabinets has been quite a journey. Never would I have guessed it would be so difficult to do something as simple as pick out how to arrange drawers. But after several weeks — plus a break for Christmas and New Year — I have a final layout, down to which drawers go where. There’s also been some interesting back and forth about what to do behind the new kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting with the cabinet layout, once I had finalized appliances and the general layout I had to get into detail. In particular figuring out how I wanted to arrange the lower cabinets. From the beginning, I’ve been pretty certain that I wanted drawers in the lower cabinets rather than doors with shelves inside. Once you’ve used a kitchen like this, you’ll never go back. I also wanted pull-outs with interior drawers. In some ways it’s a bit more inconvenient, but it looks a bit more streamlined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/basis-pullout.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Reform Basis with full-height interior pullout.&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;An example of a full-height pull-out in a different Reform option. (Photo credit: Reform)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My initial choices for interior drawers turned out not to work. I had too many drawers and the wrong choices for inserts. After much back and forth, I managed to find something that did work. I’m going with Blum’s Legrabox line of drawer boxes that has a corresponding set of organizing inserts, which should be nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/drawer-layout.png&quot; alt=&quot;Drawer layout diagram&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;My near-final attempt at coming up with a workable drawer layout for the lower cabinets.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, someone then realized that even that plan wouldn’t work. Because I’m getting the world’s fanciest German induction cooktop, there wasn’t going to be enough space to stack the oven below the cooktop. One option would’ve been to build out a super-thick worktop, to add height for the cooktop to have enough clearance over the oven. The second — what I went for — was an unexpected windfall, even if there was a slight aesthetic compromise, in the feature image at the top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/legrabox.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Blum's Legrabox system&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Blum's Legrabox drawer system. (Image credit: Blum)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to admit, the oven sitting on the right like that does look a little awkward. But there are advantages, too. I feel a lot better — given how small the space is — with an international-style 60 cm oven. I’m never going to host 30 people for Thanksgiving here. There isn’t enough space! Having a smaller oven should reduce my energy footprint. Plus, because it’s also a bit shorter than a 30” wall oven, I get a cool drawer under the oven for baking equipment. By sticking storage under the cooktop, I get that extra six inches of space, even if I can’t have a top drawer because of the cooktop’s height. It’s also a happy accident that the smaller oven is about $2,000 cheaper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cabinet order still hasn’t gone in. Because of our super fun pandemic, the delivery time has slipped to up to 18 weeks. The final price tag clocks in at about $9,500, though that includes some paneling for the area behind the newly relocated kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of, there’s been much more interesting back and forth over the newly created space in the soon-to-be former kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not exactly sure what to call the space. Maybe I’ve been watching &lt;em&gt;Grand Designs&lt;/em&gt; for too long, but I like to think of it as a mini-snug. The idea for now is to stash my piano there, thus freeing up the main living space to compensate for the intrusion of the kitchen there. It’s also a nice opportunity to make the entry to my apartment nicer. As it currently stands, coming inside is very awkward. The door sits at an angle to the walls on either side, and with such a narrow space it almost feels like you’re walking into the wall when you enter. Plus, there isn’t any storage for coats, bags, or shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/final-floorplan.png&quot; alt=&quot;Final floorplan&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The final floorplan. (Image credit: BOS | UA)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the awkwardness is resolved by tearing out the wall, so there’s ample space when you walk in the door. The storage was a bit more fun to work through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first concept was what I christened the “luxe Japanese mudroom.” It envisioned wood cladding, lots of upper storage, and what amounted to an open closet. There were a lot of great ideas. It looked very luxe and very sleek without being cold. The architects suggested using Corian for the backing and shoe shelf, which would’ve been very easy to clean. Unfortunately, I don’t have a palatial apartment where it might make sense to devote 70 square feet to an entry vestibule. Even in the render, my piano looks a little bit strange sitting in what’s effectively a closet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/entry-concept-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Initial entry concept&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The luxe Japanese mudroom concept. (Image credit: BOS | UA)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it was back to the drawing board. I suggested the Opencase system from Henrybuilt, which, while very cool, at around $10,000 for the set I wanted, was a bit outside the budget for this project. My architects came up with a very cool design that echoed that, with a pegboard system potentially wrapping two walls and into the kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really love this concept. It adds a bit of whimsy, still ties together with the kitchen — the pegboard will be made from the same material as the kitchen fronts — and gives very flexible storage. It also helps resolve my slight concern over the omission of one wall cabinet in the kitchen area, which my architects thought avoided an awkward joint at the refrigerator. I bought the argument enough to go along, but it was a little sad to give up some precious storage in a space so small. Potentially adding the peg system in the kitchen should make it possible to reclaim that as storage space, if perhaps in a way that cants more towards style than function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/pegboard-initial.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Initial pegboard entry concept&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The initial pegboard concept. (Image credit: BOS | UA)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next few weeks, the project should really get going. Or at least I suspect I’ll feel that way because I’ll have to start spending serious money. The cabinet order should go in soon, and I’m already looking at ordering the appliances to avoid delays that may exist because of the pandemic’s continued impact. I’ll probably also start getting a sense of the construction costs as we begin looking at contractors to execute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next time, there should be more details on the very cool pegboard system, and I’m planning a bit of a “staycation” to visit design showrooms. I need to pick out new flooring and begin to look at materials for the worktops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Feature image credit BOS |UA&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/cabinets-part-iv</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/cabinets-part-iv</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Cabinets, Part III</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Before spending upwards of $10,000 on something, it’s worth taking the time to see what you’re buying in person. Or at least to the extent possible in current circumstances. If it were easier to travel, I probably would have made a trip down to New York to look at complete kitchens made with Reform’s cabinet system. I’ve chosen to settle for more pandemic-friendly samples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The leading contender was Reform’s “Frame” option in white. Fortunately they had that option in stock as a sample, so I was able to get my hands on that. My architects are also big fans of natural wood, so they also pulled the “Basis” option in oak veneer for me to look at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/basis-on-white.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Basis&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The Reform Basis option. I liked the oak look more than I would've guessed. I was not as thrilled with the built-in handle.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was pleasantly surprised with the oak veneer finish. My inclination is against lots and lots of natural wood. I couldn’t articulate exactly why. But the oak is really quite nice. Certainly much nicer than other oak effect or oak veneers I’ve seen in fancy hotel rooms or other people’s less “designed” kitchens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was unpleasantly disappointed by the integrated circular cutout handle. I love the idea of a kitchen without pulls. It’s sleeker, more compact, and presents fewer chances to catch stuff (like a headphone cable or coat). But the integrated pulls on the Basis didn’t float my boat. They’re small and a little uncomfortable. There also wasn’t a ton of attention paid to the feeling of the surface you touch. It feels like bland just-sanded-enough wood. There is no joy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks kind of cool. I could see this being a good option for something other than a kitchen that’s opened less often. Having to deal with that built-in pull every day would drive me crazy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/frame-with-book.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Frame&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The Reform Frame in white. This is positioned roughly where the new run of kitchen cabinets will sit. My apartment faces north, so everything is washed in a very painterly soft light.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At any rate, I was already much more inclined to the Frame look painted white. After living with the samples for a few days, I’ve more or less committed to it. It has the whiff of classicism that I like with a bit of a modern twist. Rather than a bog standard shaker look, it evokes it with an edgy angled frame. There’s texture as the wood grain shows through the paint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/frame-white-on-white.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Frame with quartz&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Experimenting with worktop options against an end table with a marble-effect quartz composite.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m still waiting on final pricing for the cabinets. I also need to figure out exactly how I want the drawers and doors configured. Once that’s all set, the order can go in, and the fun really begins. With a provisional delivery date, I can start the planning process (getting approval from my condo board) and pick a contractor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Feature image credit BOS |UA&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 13 Dec 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/cabinets-part-iii</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/cabinets-part-iii</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Cabinets, Part II</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;The cabinet saga continues. It’s turning out to be a surprisingly fraught question. Perhaps that makes sense given it is the biggest single expense in the whole project. On the other hand, lots of other very expensive choices were easy, be that the layout or my prospective fancy German appliances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last time, I had gotten some preliminary estimates on cabinet prices, and all but ruled out “the Germans:” Bulthaup, Poggenpohl, Leicht, SieMatic. I was still waiting on firmer pricing from them, as well as pricing from a few more options. I’ll get into where I’m thinking in a moment. First, I want to do a bit of public service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/reform-frame.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Reform Frame&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Reform's Frame series in white (Image credit: Reform)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back when I was doing this project on my own, I found it somewhat maddening that none of the really high-end cabinet companies gave even a hint of what their prices were online or even when I went to visit a showroom in a couple of cases. So I’m going to quickly list out some of the prices that my architects pulled for this project. I’m hoping that Google indexes this page, and then the next time someone types “SieMatic pricing” into Google, they might get this page and find something that’s actually informative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Manufacturer&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Details&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Price&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Poggenpohl&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Segmento series&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;At least $50,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bulthaup&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Standard wood veneer, counters, backsplash, sink, faucet included&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$55,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;SieMatic&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Pure collection “Similaque” with laminated door edges, lighting included&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$37,200&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Leicht&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Topos wood veneer, lighting, tax, shipping, delivery included&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$37,200&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Leicht&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Fenix NTM doors, lighting, tax, shipping, delivery included&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$28,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Leicht&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Laminate doors, lighting, tax, shipping, delivery included&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$25,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Space Theory&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Laminate or natural wood veneer doors&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$22,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Custom Cabinets&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Painted wood doors&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$15,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reform&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Up with Ikea boxes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$10,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reform&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Frame with Ikea boxes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$10,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reform&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Degree with Ikea boxes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$7,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reform&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Basis with Ikea boxes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$5,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve left out the option I’m probably going to choose — Reform cabinet boxes with Reform fronts — because I’m still not sure the pricing on that option is exactly right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of, as these prices suggest, I’m not going to be getting my cabinets from one of the German brands. To keep to my overall $40,000 budget, the cabinets need to sit somewhere around $10,0000, and even the cheapest option from Leicht is more than twice that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that I’ve seen some samples of the Reform options (at this point only in photos, but hopefully in the flesh soon!), and they’re quite nice. In my mind, the biggest disadvantage of their system relative to the more expensive ones is flexibility: they can’t make boxes in totally custom sizes to use up every last inch of space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/ikea.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Ikea cabinet displays&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Ikea's cabinet boxes on display with transparent fronts to show off the hardware. They're using white-label Blum Tandembox, which, while nice, is not as good as the Blum Legrabox system.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the plus side, the Reform first-party cabinet boxes use Blum’s top-of-the-line Legrabox drawer system, the same set of drawer runners that all the really high-end companies use. The only real sacrifice there is a few millimeters here and there: Poggenpohl uses their own drawer boxes that are 8 mm thick rather than the Blum Legrabox system at a comparatively gigantic 12 mm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/november-white.png&quot; alt=&quot;The current concept in white&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The current layout thought in white. They've added in my real appliances (at least the ones that will be visible) and some touches like the idea of adding an uplight rather than a second level of upper cabinets. (Image credit: BOS|UA)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choice of cabinets will also guide a lot of the timing. Assuming I go with one of the Reform options, that will take about 3-4 months to manufacture and ship over from Denmark. The idea, then, is to iron out the remaining details as part of the design, find a contractor, get approvals, and then begin work so that when the cabinets arrive everything is ready for them to go in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My architects seem to think that a wood finish would look good. I’m leaning more towards something in a solid color. I don’t know that I have any sort of principled argument, other than I find a solid color more to my taste. I’m also slightly reneging on my appliance choices: after giving it some thought, I think I want a 30” cooktop after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/november-wood.png&quot; alt=&quot;The current concept in oak&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The same as above, but in an oak veneer rather than a painted finish. (Image credit: BOS|UA)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that’s all still up in the air. I’m hoping within the next few weeks I can have all the basic layout and cabinet choices made so this can really get going. Much as I don’t love the idea of living with dust everywhere, the road to a better kitchen will have to begin with a little bit of demolition.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 28 Nov 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/cabients-part-ii</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/cabients-part-ii</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Cabinets Are Expensive</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;When we left off, I had been asked to choose a layout. There was the more conservative option — leaving the kitchen in place and slightly reorganizing — versus the bolder option of creating an office with a linear kitchen in my living room. After some consideration, I decided to go down the linear kitchen route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The area where the new cabinets go is already dead space: I can’t put anything there because it would block access to the rest of my apartment and the kitchen. If I can fill that in, and also get a small room for a desk or my piano, that seems like a great idea. It also made a lot more sense when I realized it was possible to get rid of the island-cum-dining table. I should probably get a smaller dining table at some point, but in any case, that’s much more flexible when it’s not fixed as a set of cabinets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of which, the next choice I have to make is where to get the cabinets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cabinet choice is perhaps the most vexed question of the whole project. I’m pretty adamant about getting nice appliances, so I’m taking as a given that I’ll spend more there than most people would. Construction is more or less a fixed cost: either the plumbing is successfully configured or it’s not. As far as I’m aware, there’s no “luxury plumbing” I could buy to go in the walls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/option3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Kitchen Render&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The prospective reconfiguration. (Image credit: BOS|UA)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If money were no object, I’d get cabinets from one of the high-end German manufacturers. But it wasn’t clear exactly how much these companies charged for their products. When I went to visit places like Poggenpohl and SieMatic in the pre-architect days, they more or less refused to give me prices without fairly detailed architectural drawings. It seemed within the realm of possibility that — especially since it’s such a small kitchen — I might be able to squeeze a fancy German kitchen into my big-but-not-really-that-big roughly $40,000 budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rough estimates that my architects got were surprising. Some were more than I would’ve imagined. Others were still outside my budget, but a lot more reasonable than I would’ve guessed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two most expensive were Bulthaup — at a whopping $55,000 — and Poggenpohl. Money aside, Poggenpohl was my top pick. They are so expensive that projects have a hard floor of $50,000, and it’s hard to imagine that I’d want to get the absolute cheapest, most basic option they offer. They’re so expensive the Poggenpohl team didn’t even want to see the drawings to contemplate giving a more affordable bid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second choice, SieMatic, came in lower than I would’ve guessed, at around $25,000. My architects also looked at Leicht, which came in around the same price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/siematic-pure-010.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;SieMatic Pure&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;A SieMatic Kitchen I can't afford. (Image credit: SieMatic)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zooming out a little, the cabinets more or less need to cost about $10,000. With my $40,000 budget, about $10,000 will go to appliances, and the architects are working with a $10,000 figure for all the construction costs, like moving the plumbing and moving walls. With $10,000 spent on cabinets, that leaves a further $10,000 for other finishes like worktops and lighting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus: the final option on the table is the “IKEA hack.” In particular, my architects have proposed going with Reform, a company out of Copenhagen that offers “designer” fronts for IKEA cabinet shells. That looks like it will fall somewhere closer to $7500 for the options that looked the most promising to me. I should get a quote from Space Theory in the next few days as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/fold.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Reform Degree&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Reform's Degree design. (Image credit: Reform)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a way, I find this comforting. I worry that I’m spending way, way too much money on fancy appliances. But even if I go down to more “conventional” choices for my oven or refrigerator, I still wouldn’t be able to afford one of my fancy German cabinet options. It seems possible I might even get the project in under $40,000, which could leave some latitude for buying some extra fancy lighting or laundry appliances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I have this narrowed down a bit, there will be more renders to finalize the design, and then it comes down to scheduling. Finding a contractor will depend a lot on the point at which I can take delivery of the cabinets at the core of the design.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/cabients-are-expensive</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/cabients-are-expensive</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>