<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Renovation Diary</title>
        <description>Joseph renovates his kitchen.</description>
        <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/</link>
        <atom:link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2022 07:34:30 -0600</pubDate>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2022 07:34:30 -0600</lastBuildDate>
        <generator>Jekyll v4.0.1</generator>
        
            <item>
                <title>Panel Installation</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;The project continues to inch toward the finish line. Yesterday, they began installing the wood panels in what was the kitchen area. It’s a surprisingly delicate and complicated ballet of pieces that need to line up due to the perforations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, they had to install the floating steel shelves. Having lugged two of them up from the basement when they were delivered, they are astonishingly heavy. Installed, they have that fun feeling of defying gravity. I’m a little less excited about the fact they cut holes in the newly finished and painted wall to fit them in. That’s not going to be a fun patch job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/panels-opening.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Through the opening&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Looking through the kitchen wall, it's a bit easier to see the floating steel shelves&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The panels themselves aren’t quite done. But they made a ton of progress, and it’s beginning to look good. Once again, I find myself in the interesting position where I take photos and it looks so like the renders that I looked at almost two years ago in the design phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/panels-detail.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Panel detail&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The thick flying wall that backs the kitchen cabinets will get an end cap mirror to add light and a feeling of space&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what I’ve been told, they won’t be back until Monday to finish the panels. The other big blocker is the solid surface cladding that will form the countertops, backsplash, and caps around the upper cabinets. Once that’s in, the plumbing and electrical get get wrapped up, as the sink, faucet, and appliances all interface with those pieces in some way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2022 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/panels</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/panels</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Painting, Part III</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;The painters made another trip and wrapped up their work. It’s nice to be another step closer to having my home back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the vast quantity of home renovation media teaches us anything, it’s that an image or video conceals many sins when it comes to painting. Which is to say, I found it difficult to convey the sense of progress the painting has given when you’re on the site in person. It feels a lot more finished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/painting-hall-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Looking down the hall&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;All the marigold paint is now gone&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most visibly, all the ceiling scars have been patched, sanded, and painted. I’m trying not to get too hung up on the details: it looks a lot better now. Without knowing where the old walls came down, I doubt anyone could point to where the patches have been done. The fresh coat of paint on the ceiling makes a surprisingly big difference, as I may have noted earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/ceiling-patched.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ceiling&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Virtually impossible to tell where the ceiling damage was&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crew also patched a hole in the bathroom wall, painted the new baseboard in my bedroom, and fixed my error with a coat of flat paint over the eggshell. It’s still drying, so it doesn’t have the delicious velvety feel quite yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m really hoping the contractor can keep this momentum up. Aside from the punch list, we’re down to only a few major jobs. They need to install the CNC panels in the old kitchen space, which gets most of the remaining material off the floor. All the Corian needs to be installed. Once that’s done, they can finish the plumbing and electric, and I think we’re close to done.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2022 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/painting-iii</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/painting-iii</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Painting, Part II</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;The painters have been back and continue to make progress. I made one small mistake that hopefully isn’t too hard to remediate. Most dramatically, they’ve gotten the plywood ready for the millwork installation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My error was one of omission. A few years ago I repainted most of my apartment myself over a few weekends. After much debate, I used Farrow and Ball “Strong White,” which I thought struck a nice balance between coolness and intensity. (My initial idea to use their “All White” was very instructive. The intensity of that nearly seared my retinas.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than have the painters start from scratch, I figured it would be easiest to repaint in the same color. But I failed to mention that I wanted Farrow and Ball’s flat finish paint, rather than eggshell. I’m hoping they need to come back for a second coat after sanding, and can correct this without too much of a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The repairs to wall and ceiling damage continues as well. It’s looking good. While they still have more work to do, it’s a lot better than it was. In a few places, aside from the fact it hasn’t been painted yet, all the construction scars are completely gone now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/painting-black.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Plywood painted black&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The two panel walls got a coat of black paint before the panels get attached&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In anticipation of the millwork installation next week, the plywood panels have gotten their coat of black paint. It’s made the old kitchen space a lot more dramatic. Fortunately it won’t be quite as dark once the millwork goes in on top. Though I do kind of like the look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next week I’m hoping they can finish the painting, get the millwork installed, and, if they can get the countertops installed too, the project may actually get wrapped up. Or at the very least, I may have a working kitchen again.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/painting-ii</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/painting-ii</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Painting Begins</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Progress has resumed with a few visits from the painting crew. Their work is an object lesson in the value of painting and the benefit of hiring true professionals to do the work. No, painting isn’t that difficult. But it’s clear that people who do this for a living know what they’re doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s largely preparation at this point. They’re filling holes, doing patches, caulking and otherwise getting all the surfaces ready to receive the paint. It’s weirdly satisfying to finally see the last vestiges of the previous owner’s marigold paint get covered with primer. It wasn’t my favorite color. I never painted over it because I knew — eventually — I’d do this bigger project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/painting-hall.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Priming over marigold paint&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Primer goes on the last parts of my apartment still in the marigold that the previous owner had chosen&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amount of artistry that goes into some parts of this process amazes me. Around the old kitchen walls, the ceiling looks pretty dire. Seeing the supplies and sheer quantity of filler required to patch and repair those wounds is fascinating. From what the painting crew said, it will take another day or two to finish up that work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/painting-patch.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Patching the ceiling&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Initial patching work to repair the ceiling scars&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the less damaged parts of the ceiling, you can begin to see the light at the end of the tunnel. I never would have guessed that repainting the ceiling would make such a huge difference, and yet, it really does look a lot better. I may have to get a painting crew (or spend a weekend) doing the same in my bedroom after this project gets wrapped up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/painting-ceiling.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ceiling painting&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;A fresh coat of flat white paint on the ceiling&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking ahead, there’s still more painting to do. The plywood that closed the two walls behind the new kitchen needs to get a coat of black paint, to disappear behind the white perforated panels. The real constraint are the countertops, which would then let the finish plumbing and electrical happen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/painting</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/painting</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Closing</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;The building inspector gave clearance on closing the two remaining walls. It’s a tantalizing taste of progress. On the other hand, there are still a few remaining hiccups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the last two walls will get the fun CNC milled panels installed, they’ve gotten covered with sheets of plywood rather than plasterboard. It’s an interesting look. I could see it working as a final finish if a bit more care was taken with the pattern of plywood sheets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a near miss with the plumbing, though. When the plumber came to do his work initially, he added shutoff valves to my plumbing, presumably to make it easier to do the plumbing work without needing to shut down the water for all my neighbors. That hadn’t been turned back on before the walls were closed. Fortunately I caught it before the panels had gone up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, there are a few issues to work out on the appliance install that’s precluding the countertop fabrication and installation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m hopeful that we’re actually getting to the end.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/closing</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/closing</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Not Quite</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday the contractor was on site again, which was at least superficially exciting. As ever, I got home last night with a bit of trepidation as well. That emotion proved to be warranted. While they tried to install the appliances, they did not succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting with the dishwasher, the layer of sound insulating material on the top has been removed. It’s also been installed too far back. On a practical level, if the (required) front cabinet panel were installed, it wouldn’t be possible to open the appliance. On an aesthetic level, the front of the dishwasher is supposed to align with the rest of the cabinets, so it blends in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/appliances-dishwasher-install.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dishwasher in place&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Missing? The layer of sound insulation that used to be on top. Also note that, if you were to put on the required front cabinet panel, you wouldn't be able to open the appliance.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s fun to finally see my amazing new oven out of its crating. It’s less fun to see it installed the way it is. It was supposed to sit on a shelf, so that the small drawer could sit underneath. We even ordered a ventilated shelf and some super strong brackets to hold the weight of the appliance. Instead, the oven was placed in the bottom of the cabinet, and someone thought it would be a good idea to unilaterally move the drawer to the top. A location where I don’t think it’s going to fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/appliances-oven-front.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Oven installed&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The oven is supposed to be installed on a shelf so the drawer, previously installed correctly, could sit below&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being able to open the oven is exciting, though. It’s a very nice piece of hardware. I love the 60 cm design the rest of the world uses, so the trays slide right into the side runners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/appliances-oven-open.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Oven interior&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;On the plus side, I'm very excited to use my new oven&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The refrigerator-freezer is perhaps the most frustrating and perplexing. It’s so obviously wrong, it makes me wonder what the people installing it were thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/appliances-fridge-gap.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Refrigerator gap&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The refrigerator-freezer is supposed to be pushed all the way in, so it lines up with the other cabinets&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most obviously, it’s sticking out several inches from the cabinet. As with the dishwasher, the idea is that it sits flush with the cabinets, so it blends in and you don’t see it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/appliances-refrigerator-open.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Open refrigerator&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;It's a nice appliance, in any case&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thumbing through the very detailed installation guide created other moments of confusion. The bright red clips labeled “Transport only” on the doors, designed to keep the appliance safe during shipping, haven’t been removed. The plastic filler piece at the top of the appliance has been crushed and shoved into the cabinet, rather than set up to cover the small gap between the top of the refrigerator-freezer and the shelf above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to mention, after the bottom of the appliance’s cabinet box was erroneously cut off, they didn’t add the remedial vent cutouts to ensure the refrigeration circuit gets the airflow it needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, they’re going to have to make another trip to fix it. I’m also still waiting to finalize the countertops, and the inspector still needs to make another visit to sign off on the fire sprinkler work.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/not-quite</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/not-quite</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Caséta Interlude</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;As the days get shorter and the project remains uncompleted, it’s gotten more annoying that there’s no way to turn on a light when I get home without stumbling in the dark. Last week, I decided to do something about it by setting up a &lt;a href=&quot;http://casetawireless.com&quot;&gt;Lutron Caséta&lt;/a&gt; system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lutron’s Caséta system brings ideas that used to be the preserve of very expensive custom installations into the mass market. The Caséta dimmers and switches operate existing lighting circuits. They also connect to a network bridge that allows the lights to be automated in fun and interesting ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can bridge the Caséta system into Apple’s HomeKit universe (or use Lutron’s iOS application) to control the lights and program scenes with your phone. Or you can use system accessories like Lutron’s Pico remote to drop a switch anywhere (they operate over a proprietary wireless band) to control one or multiple lighting circuits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s this last part that I took advantage of to deal with my “getting home and it’s pitch black” problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I replaced a few of the switches in the unaffected parts of my apartment with Caséta dimmers. Then I set up a Pico remote to operate those circuits. The remote is cleverly the same size as a decorator-style switch, and Lutron provides a holder to retrofit it into a standard switch box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually there will be a switch next to my front door that controls a lighting circuit. For now, I’ve slipped in a Pico remote to turn on other lights to avoid tripping in the dark. It’s still not exactly great, but it’s much improved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/caseta-entry.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Caséta Pico remote&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Pico remote temporarily installed in the entry junction box&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a system, I’m impressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Caséta “universe” is incredibly reliable. Ridiculous as it sounds, this is a big deal. I’ve used the Philips Hue system before, and, nice as it is, the fact the controls fail one out of even a thousand times is a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also really appreciate that the system doesn’t solely rely on special controls or a piece of smartphone software. You can use the system as normal. The normal switches in the normal place work as normal. Normal people can operate the lights without special instructions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/caseta-dimmer.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Caséta dimmer&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;A circa 1950 switch replaced with a new Lutron Caséta dimmer&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only major downside is the system’s cost. Each of the switches runs about $60, and the cost doesn’t go down if you instead use a simple on-off switch rather than a dimmer. Plus the cost of the remotes (maddeningly, $20 for the white ones and $40 for the black ones) and the network bridge (about $100).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I’ve had to use dimmers on all my old lighting circuits because the simple on-off switches require a neutral wire. That wasn’t how they ran lighting circuits in the 1950s. If I’m honest, having dimmers everywhere is kind of nice and kind of fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a more “this would be nice” level, there are two small paper cut issues I’d love to have them address.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I really wish it were possible to change the way the lights turn on and off. I’m sure most people think the subtle fade up and fade down make the system feel more “premium.” There are places it feels weird. Like in the bathroom. It’s nice to have the ability to dim the lights. I’d really rather than simply (or more quickly) turn on and off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, it would be nice if Lutron were more open to other systems. The Pico remote is a genius concept. I’d love to be able to control devices outside Lutron’s switches or their universe of hand-selected partners.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/caseta</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/caseta</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Sprinkler Move</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;After over a month of stasis, the project is creeping back to life. The fire sprinkler company finally made it today and did the work to move the sprinkler per the building inspector’s demands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a trickier part of the build than some others. Unlike the rest of the work, the fire sprinkler was my responsibility and not something in the contractor’s purview. So I had to do all the coordination on this myself, with help from the architectural practice I’m working with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s good they were around to support. If not for some help, they would have routed the sprinkler in a very strange path that wouldn’t have looked too great. As it is, I’m fine living with the sprinkler head peeping out over the top of the upper cabinets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/sprinkler-moved.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Relocated fire sprinkler&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Relocated to cover the new cooktop&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the plus side, the fire sprinkler contractors said that I didn’t need to keep a sprinkler head in the new entry area, so that’s one less ugly bit sticking out of the wall. It should make the finish a lot neater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here, the contractor should be unblocked. I have no idea what the timeline or order of events is, but I’m hoping they get a move on.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/sprinkler</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/sprinkler</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Delivery</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Progress continues to inch along. The builders were back doing some electrical work and continuing to work on the cabinets. Tantalizingly, after a slight hiccup last week I finally got my appliances delivered. A step toward completion, even if I can’t use them yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The electricians were back on site to start preparing for the second fix. Most of the wiring is now in place for the final boxes and connections to be made at the panel. I’m less clear why they punched a couple of holes in the that had been plastered. They’re not exactly attractive. I’m hoping they get covered up later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/mystery-holes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Holes in the wall&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;It's not totally clear why they cut these two holes into the plastered back wall&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work also continued on the cabinets. They were re-aligned so that the fridge-freezer will be in-plane with the rest of the base cabinets. Holes were cut into the tops for the eventual installation of the cooktop and sink. They left the sink in the cutout, which is fun to see. It’s obviously not plumbed in, but there’s something about it that helps me feel the progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also finally got my appliances delivered. I think they’re a ways off installing them, but it’s great to see them on site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/appliances-boxed.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Appliances in boxes&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The appliances in their boxes&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, I’m not entirely sure what’s next. Here’s hoping they can get the bulk of it done by the end of the month.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 03 Sep 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/delivery</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/delivery</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Ups and Downs</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;As seems to be the pattern, there has been some encouraging progress this week, but with some asterisks. They installed most of the cabinet fronts and started the plaster. It’s starting to really look finished. A few of the details are giving the progress a bit of a sour note, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the plus side, there was a lot of progress. The drawers and base cabinet fronts are in. Those Blum drawer runners are truly a joy and feel worth every penny. Drawers on base cabinets are the way to go. If you don’t look too hard, it all looks pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/cabinet-doors-overall.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cabinets with doors&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;From  a distance, it looks pretty reasonable&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In person, though, I find the installation at this stage a bit disappointing. I knew that I wouldn’t get the millimeter-precise alignment of cabinets from someone like SieMatic by going this more budget-friendly route, but I still feel like the alignment of the doors could be better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/cabinet-flaw-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A cabinet door&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;It certainly looks to me like they drilled through the face of the cabinet and patched it&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More worrying to me, there are clear installation defects that, at least to my eyes, go beyond usual issues. To my eyes, it really looks like the face of one of the doors got drilled through and patched. It’s not a great look. The fact that the hinges also don’t sit cleanly and flush in the back of the doors, and that there was clearly tear out when they drilled out the hinge cups, gives me pause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I wind up having to replace the damaged doors, I don’t want to think about the lead time on those parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/cabinet-flaw-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Back of a cabinet door&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;More worrying details on the back of the cabinet doors&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plastering got started, too. Aside from the inevitable mess, I’m pretty happy with the way it looks. It’s beginning to make the space feel more finished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/plaster-back.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Plaster going in&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The first coat of plaster going in on the back wall&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving forward, I’m still waiting on the fire sprinkler permit and, after a false start, the appliances should get delivered next week.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/ups-and-downs</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/ups-and-downs</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>