<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Renovation Diary</title>
        <description>Joseph remodels his kitchen.</description>
        <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/</link>
        <atom:link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2020 18:03:41 -0500</pubDate>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2020 18:03:41 -0500</lastBuildDate>
        <generator>Jekyll v4.0.1</generator>
        
            <item>
                <title>Resurrection</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been almost three years since I bought my apartment with the idea of renovating the kitchen, and I still haven’t done anything beyond install a new dishwasher. The first hurdle was getting the money together. Even my tiny kitchen with modest upgrades is going to be fairy expensive. Then, of course, the world was hit with a pandemic. Stuck at home and without the ability to really travel or visit friends, I didn’t love the idea of living on a construction site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I realized we could be in this situation for a very long time, however. It’s time to take the leap and begin the renovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve set up this new blog to keep a running diary of the process. I’m hoping to keep interested people informed with a difference. Yes, I’ll have the usual photos and commentary of the process as it goes along. But I’m also going to be very honest about details that a lot of people seem to skim over. Living on a construction site isn’t fun, and major home renovations are not cheap. It’s misleading to imagine that you can achieve Architectural Digest-quality with pluck and elbow grease. I’ll spend more on my architects than you’d pay for a high-end watch or fancy handbag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m hoping that by chronicling all the little details most people omit, this will be a more interesting and a more useful guide for anyone else hoping to take on a project like mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my next post, I’ll piece together more of a project update recapping where I am today, and what’s happening as I dust off the project and get it moving again. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/resurrection</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/resurrection</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>