<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Renovation Diary</title>
        <description>Joseph renovates his kitchen.</description>
        <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/</link>
        <atom:link href="https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2022 20:32:09 -0500</pubDate>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2022 20:32:09 -0500</lastBuildDate>
        <generator>Jekyll v4.0.1</generator>
        
            <item>
                <title>Framing</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;The renovation continues, and appears to have hit its first hiccup. The framing started today, which was exciting. Then I got home and began scratching my head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in the design phase, my architects specified a non-standard wall to back the run of cabinets. To let light into the former kitchen, it doesn’t go up to the ceiling and there’s an opening behind the sink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/cabinet-final.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cabinet render&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The vision (credit: BOS | UA)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus my confusion when I got home and noticed that the framing for the new wall goes up to the ceiling. That, it turns out, was probably a mistake. I have some faith that it will get fixed, but it has to be said that it’s a little annoying. I was so excited when I left the house today!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/framing-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;What was the kitchen&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The former kitchen&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the plus side, seeing the walls at least approximately in the right place is encouraging. The former kitchen entry area is definitely small, but it’s a surprisingly nice space, all things considered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/framing-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Looking back&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/framing</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/framing</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Demolition</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;The project has begun! More through coincidence than any real planning, I was able to have the first step — demolition — take place while I was out of town. It was pretty surreal to come home to a construction site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of, it’s definitely going to be a struggle. There is dust everywhere. So much that I saturated the medium particle filter in my vacuum cleaner after 20 minutes of trying to clear up the dust all over the place. If I hadn’t had an air purifier running in my bedroom, it’s scary to think how much more dust there would have been for me to clean up. I’m resigned to having to replace the filter far sooner than six months from now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/demolition-zipwall.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Drawings&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Zipwalls help, but they're far from a panacea for keeping dust out of the non-work areas&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/demolition-drawing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Drawings&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The architect managing my project thought it would be a good idea to cover the windows in protective plastic, and then someone unplugged the power to my old iPhone anyway, so I don’t have any time-lapse footage of the demolition. I’m working on rigging something up in a location that works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s kind of fun to see some of the old finishes that previous inhabitants of the apartment have tried out. Having wallpaper in the kitchen (especially one so small) doesn’t seem like a great idea to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/demolition-wallpaper.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Old wallpaper&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/demolition-wallpaper-red.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;More old wallpaper&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Not a pattern I'd put in a kitchen&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also fun to finally understand some of the construction details of the building. On some level, I understand that I basically live in a concrete box. Seeing it makes a difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/demolition-beam.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Beam detail&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The demolition has finally uncovered how the interior, non-load bearing walls of my apartment were constructed. They’re weirdly thin — around 3” rather than the typical 5” — and definitely not constructed with modern materials like wood framing and gypsum wall board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had assumed it was lath and plaster with ancient wiring, but was surprised to discover it’s something else entirely. From what I can see, it looks like they substituted a kind of metal mesh for the lath, and then did infill with what looks like thinset cement, which was then given a skim coat of plaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/demolition-wall-detail.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wall detail&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;An interesting lath and plaster alternative&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d always wondered how the electrical lines were run, again, given that the structure of my building is cast concrete. Maybe not surprisingly, everything was run through metal conduits. It makes me somewhat less optimistic that it would be easy to do something like run new wiring for an additional ceiling light. It goes without saying, cutting a channel into cast concrete is not a walk in the park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/demolition-hanging-wire.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A dangling light switch&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/demolition-conduit-box.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;One way to do an outlet&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 09 Apr 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/demolition</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/demolition</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>The End of the Beginning</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s really happening: the demolition for the new kitchen begins on Tuesday next week. And it’s been even more of a mad dash to make sure that happened, and that everything was in place for it to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in the last post, once the contractor got the permit, it was really a race to get everything in place. With no small amount of stress and scrambling, I managed to thread that needle. The movers showed up on time to pick up the larger pieces of furniture, and I spent evenings and the two weekends bringing box after box to my basement storage unit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a lot of work. I told myself that only packing up part of my apartment wouldn’t be as bad as a full-on move, and I’m not sure I was right. I used almost all the boxes I had saved from the last time I moved, and my basement storage unit is pretty full.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s an accretion effect: none of the tasks to get my apartment ready for construction was really that onerous, but put together, it was a lot. Going on a brutalist adventure to city hall to get a parking permit — necessary when you need to put the permit up the same day — only took about an hour. But then it also took an hour to pack and transport a few boxes down to the basement. It really adds up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s done, and a crew will show up on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still need to drop letters off to all my neighbors. And, assuming I don’t get sucked into any meetings on Monday, I’ll pop in to the project kick off with the architects and contractor’s team.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/end-of-the-beginning</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/end-of-the-beginning</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>The Permit Dash</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;For once, some good news on the project: my contractor got the permit way ahead of schedule. On the other hand, I wasn’t really prepared for them to get it so quickly. It was supposed to take about a month from contract signature; it wound up taking about two days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took about a week of back-and-forth with my building manager to get the sign off from my condo association for the project. At which point, the contractor applied for the permit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we were going over the contract, it was explained to me that it would take about 30 days to get the permit. Not because it had to, but because that’s the time limit the City of Boston operates under, and, in my team’s experience, they usually took the whole window.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus my immense surprise when, two days later, I got a phone call from the contractor that the permit was approved, and they were ready to go. I got the impression they could’ve started the next morning had I been ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before they start, however, I’m going to have to move all my stuff out of the work area. Most of this will go elsewhere in my apartment or my building. I have basement storage in the basement, and I bought a $20 Ikea garment rack to hold my clothes in the (relative) safety of my bedroom. That’s been my weekend project, hauling one box of stuff down to the basement after another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stickier issue is getting the larger pieces of furniture out, like my dining table. That really won’t fit anywhere else, and so I needed to find a moving and storage company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I keep thinking there’s a business opportunity buried in the madness of finding movers, in the same way I found the process of finding a contractor so fraught. If there’s anything even remotely non-standard about your move, no one reads the notes, and the estimate doesn’t seem to take the details into account. Plus there’s all the other complication of having to get a parking permit from the city and from my condo association to make sure the move is allowed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I’ve found movers, a nice technology-forward company called Small Haul, that focuses on small moving jobs, and who (blessedly) has a storage partner that isn’t at capacity. I didn’t have the presence of mind to clear the date with the people who manage my building, so it’s looking like it will be a mad dash on Monday morning to get the details ironed out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m really pushing to get the work going in two weeks, when I have a good excuse not to be at home while they’re getting going and doing the demolition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has also been an interesting test of the project management stance of the system. With so many people and so many parts in motion, I can see how communication is vital. The architect managing my project suggested we have a weekly check-in meeting, and I’m beginning to see the value in that, to make sure information flows well between the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Feature image credit BOS |UA&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 26 Mar 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/permit-dash</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/permit-dash</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Contract Signature</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;It is done! Today I got the contract and signed. I’ll also get the first payment in the mail to the contractor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wound up going for what I thought was a reasonably modern experience. The architect shepherding my project prepared the standard A105 (a standard contract for small projects), which was first executed by the contractor, and then given to me for signature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here, I need to mail the contractor a check for the first payment. At that point, they’ll get going on the permitting process, which formally gates the construction beginning in earnest. That’s supposed to take about 30 days, and then adding the three months of construction, the project should be substantially complete around the middle of July.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in the last post, this included a not-so-fun extra $1,000 or so for an additional chunk of wall to facilitate the necessary electrical upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final contract’s cost breakdown was:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Item&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Cost&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Permitting&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$810&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;General conditions&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$7,428.24&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Preparation and demolition&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$3,645&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Carpentry (including flooring material)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$18,250&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Electrical&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$14,842.25&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Plumbing&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$7,672&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Patching and painting&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$4,290&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Countertops&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$11,853.70&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among those costs, a few were broken out to account for potential variance. This is meant to make it fairer should one of the more speculative items cost more or less than anticipated. For instance, I really hope running a new feeder wire does not do $1,000 in damage to the common areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flooring: $4,800&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fire sprinkler changes: $900&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Painting and patching common areas: $1,000&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Countertop material: $5,692&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is then broken out into a payment schedule based on milestones, which someone from my architect’s office will assess and gate payment for as part of their construction administration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Payment 1: Contract signature: $9,015.72&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Payment 2: Work begins: $17,462.89&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Payment 3: First fix electrical and plumbing plus framing: $16,146.39&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Payment 4: After millwork installation: $8,843.90&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Payment 5: After flooring is installed plus second fix plumbing and electrical: $10,322.80&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Payment 6: After final inspections and completion: $7,000.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now my attention turns to finding somewhere to store all of my large furniture when the project is moving. The clock is ticking!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/signature</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/signature</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Bidding, Part IV</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;The good news: I have the final contract, potentially ready to sign. As ever, though, it has been a lesson in the perils of doing a construction project. Or perhaps more specifically, a fairly high-specification construction project in a difficult site in a historic neighborhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I write this, I’m ready to sign. My architects set me and the contractor up with an A105, which I’m informed is a pretty standard contract for smaller architect-led projects. Most importantly in my mind, it does a more precise job laying out how the architect interfaces with the owner and contractor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s taken about a week to hash out some final details. I’m less clear what’s gone on from the contractor’s side. From my end, there was some additional insurance I didn’t realize I didn’t have because of the strange way my condo association buys insurance for my whole building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contractor needs to execute the document first, and then I’ll execute, and we’re ready to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the saga of the electrical upgrade continues. The potential feeder wire replacement was not enough. Now it seems that they’ll have to build out a new wall (confusingly, in front of an existing wall) to contain the new electrical panel and feeder wiring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This adds another $1,000 or so to the project cost, which I’m not exactly thrilled about. On the other hand, I knew what I was getting into, and I’m not completely surprised this (and many other unexpected costs) have emerged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does make me appreciate how renovation projects wind up being diluted by the time they’re completed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are places where it’s really not possible to scrimp. While annoying, it would be far worse to have a completed project that fails inspection than to cut elsewhere in the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, it’s very clear exactly where people would scrimp. Buying that $300 dishwasher instead of the $1000 dishwasher almost pays for the unexpected wall construction. Downgrading the flooring material to vinyl plank that goes for $4 per square foot instead of high-spec, $10 per square foot engineered hardwood would come close to covering the cost of running a new feeder wire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s something very disappointing about the idea of putting in so much work, only to have it fall down on the details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Feature image credit BOS |UA&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 12 Mar 2022 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/bid-iv</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/bid-iv</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Bidding, Part III</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m almost at the end of the bidding process. It hasn’t exactly ended the way I’d hoped, but then the last two years have changed my expectations pretty considerably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contract still isn’t quite ready to sign, but I’m very close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one big outstanding question has been resolved: I’m going to have to replace the feeder wire to my electrical panel at a cost of around $5,000. Reading between the lines, the city wasn’t able to grandfather me in with 75 amp service. It’s unfortunate from a cost perspective, though on the other hand, gives me lots of headroom for my menagerie of electrical appliances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My architects have also consulted with the prospective contractor to trim out any unnecessary expenses. It hasn’t amounted to much relative to the total bill. They’ve cut out expenses like a few hundred dollars to run a water line to my fridge-freezer, which doesn’t need one, as it doesn’t have an ice maker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, I think this goes to show the value of having experts combing through the details. The small amount of time spent scrutinizing the plans has saved far more than the cost of those professional services. Of course, I’m very aware that hiring an architect (or, let’s be honest, my aesthetic aspirations) probably increased the cost of the project in making it less straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next week I’ll coordinate scheduling and dates. My architects have also said they’ll draw up a standard AIA (American Institute of Architects) owner-contractor agreement, rather than the document provided by my prospective contractor. I’ll probably have more to say about that once I’ve seen it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it stands now, the quote breaks down like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Item&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Cost&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Permitting&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$810&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;General conditions&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$7,400&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Preparation and demolition&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$3,600&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Carpentry (including flooring material)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$17,300&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Electrical&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$14,800&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Plumbing&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$7,800&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Patching and painting&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$4,300&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Countertops&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$11,900&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding that up (and rounding slightly) brings the whole cost of the kitchen construction and materials to a cool $67,900. Adding the bathroom would pull that up another $22,400 in the itemized bid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nor is that going to be the total cost. I’ve already spent almost $17,000 on the cabinets and professional fees. (Though some of that is pre-paying for construction administration.) And I’ll need to add another $11,000 for appliances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That will bring this whole project in at close to $90,000. A staggering sum of money, if I’m honest. And almost exactly double the original budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be back next week with more on the actual execution, scheduling, and taking the plunge.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2022 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/bid-iii</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/bid-iii</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Feeder Wire</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m very close to signing a contract to get the program going. The last detail: pinning down the cost of the electrical work. In particular, the core upgrades necessary for the increased load that the renovation will put on the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went into the project knowing that I’d need to upgrade the panel. For starters, I’m adding enough new circuits I need a new panel simply for space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Current code requires more loads go on separate circuits for safety. More importantly, I’m adding a bunch of new appliances: a separate oven and cooktop (rather than the existing all-in-one range), each of which need a double-gang slot to carry 240 V to those appliances; and then a washer and dryer. Fortunately, the Miele heat pump dryer that I’ve specified only requires a 15 amp circuit, but each laundry appliance does need to go on its own separate circuit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relatively straightforward panel replacement had already been factored into the bid. But there was an additional twist that needed additional following up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these new appliances also require more overall capacity on the panel. My current service to the apartment is only 60 amps, common when my building was built in the 1950s, but well below current standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the electrician, the existing feeder wire — the wire that runs from the electric meter to my apartment — can only safely carry 75 amps. That’s enough to support all the new electrical load I’m putting on the system, but below the 100 amp minimum that code currently requires for a dwelling of any size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question then is whether it will be possible to have my system grandfathered in. If it can be, that’s a huge savings: there’s no additional work to do. If it can’t, then the electrician will need to run a new feeder wire from my apartment to the meter. I haven’t seen pricing, but there’s no way that’s going to be inexpensive. The meter is about 100 feet down the common corridor from my apartment, and the new wire won’t run in a completely straight line. Moreover, it will have to run through a conduit buried in a cast concrete slab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it has to happen, I don’t have much choice but to pay for it. I also don’t envy the person who has to do the work.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 12 Feb 2022 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/feeder-wire</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/feeder-wire</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Bidding, Part II</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Almost six months ago, I accepted my fate: this project is going to cost a lot more than I had hoped and anticipated. On the plus side, I’ve been waiting so long, I’m in a position to do that somewhat comfortably. But that doesn’t remove the feeling that everything is just that little bit out of reach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After getting a bid roughly double the original labor and materials estimate, I figured it would at least be worth exploring what it would cost to do “everything,” meaning mostly adding a gut remodel of the apartment’s bathroom to my project scope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the week, the contractor visited again to finalize pricing on that, and I think it’s pushed me to make some decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the good news: my contractor is ready to go. It’s likely the kitchen portion of my project will get going next month, in March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bad news: it’s still very expensive. The latest bid for both my kitchen renovation and the gut remodel of the bathroom comes to a cool $81,000 or so. I think it’s important to share that number. There’s something deeply frustrating about seeing all these renovation projects on TV or on blogs, and the authors making it seem like pluck and effort are the reason you don’t live in an Instagram-ready home. This stuff is expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That $81,000 isn’t the totality of the project’s cost either. I’ve already spent around $10,000 on cabinets (still hanging out in a warehouse somewhere in New Jersey), and doing the kitchen and bathroom would require about $10,000 worth of appliances, another $5,000 for bathroom fixtures, and then some amount for me to relocate while my apartment is being ripped apart. Add that up and the total cost comes to around $100,000. Put differently: more than I’d like to spend right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plus: there are a few more smaller tweaks I’d like to make — adding wardrobe space in the bedroom, replacing some very bland millwork in the living space — that would add even more to that number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s still some finalization to be done, but for anyone interested, the contract as currently specified looks something like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$810 for permitting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$3,100 for project management&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$4,300 for site preparation and demolition&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$20,000 for carpentry&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$11,300 for electrical&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$15,800 for plumbing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$2,700 for drywall work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$3,400 for painting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$20,500 for tile and counters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having never done this before, I was also interested to understand much more specifically when and how the cost is spread over the duration of the contract. If you’re curious too, the breakdown looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Around 10% at contract signature&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Around 25% when work begins&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Around 20% when framing plus rough-in (first fix) plumbing and electric is completed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Around 15% after the cabinets and tile are in&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Around 15% after flooring and second fix plumbing and electric is completed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Around 15% after final inspections and completion of work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I can’t really swing dropping $100,000 right now, the thought is to break the project into two phases: do the kitchen now, and then do the bathroom maybe a year from now after my finances have had a chance to recover. Based on the earlier bid, I’m hoping that I can get the kitchen-only portion down to around $55,000, putting me somewhere like $65,000 including the appliances I’ll buy myself. It’s a lot of money, but I’m in the fortunate position that I can spend that pretty comfortably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should have an update next week on exactly what comes of that. I’m a little nervous, to be sure. Home renovations are notorious for being stressful, complicated, and running over budget. But after the very unpleasant experience buying my apartment — which really was at the absolute limits of what I could afford at the time — I’m very happy choosing the slightly more conservative path. Spending $65,000 is a pretty dizzying concept. But I also have the money, and enough beyond that set aside for a pretty catastrophic worst-case scenario.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/bid-ii</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/bid-ii</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>At a Crossroads</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;The pandemic has thrown a wrench in just about every part of this project. Getting information from the potential cabinet companies took forever. It took forever to order the cabinets. It took forever to get the cabinets delivered and shipped. It took forever to even get me flooring samples when we got to that stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then it took forever to find a contractor. The last six months, more or less, and not for lack of trying. The results of that process have thrown a wrench in the project. Either way, it’s going to be a lot more expensive than I had hoped. Thanks, pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, a few steps back. A few years ago, when I bought this apartment, I had poorly-informed delusions about how much such a project might cost. In retrospect, the thought I could do anything meaningful for $25,000 was laughable. After a few years of savings and a bit of re-calibration, I landed on a more realistic figure of $45,000 for the project when I brought it back to life a year ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/siematic-pure-010.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;SieMatic Pure&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;A SieMatic Kitchen I can't afford. (Image credit: SieMatic)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working to that figure has been a strong input to the process. It’s the reason I bought cabinets from Reform rather than, say, SieMatic as I’d hoped might just maybe be affordable. (If you haven’t read &lt;a href=&quot;cabients-part-ii&quot;&gt;that post&lt;/a&gt;, they very much were not even remotely within my budget.) It was equally reassuring that my architects had done a project along the same lines in 2019 that had construction costs in line with that sort of budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the pandemic threw a wrench in all that. Accounting for the cabinets and appliances, that left around $25,000 for construction and materials. Not a trivial sum! The bids my architects got blew that out of the water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first was for roughly $44,000. The second was for close to $50,000, nearly double the budgeted amount. The third wouldn’t even give a precise estimate, from what I heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it was conveyed to me, several pieces contributed to these astronomical quotes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, supply chain issues. In the design my architects put together, the worktops and backsplash are designed to be made out of Corian. The counters need to be in half-inch because they need to support the work of cooking. But the backsplash and protective caps on the upper cabinets don’t, and could be made of (much cheaper) quarter-inch Corian. The quarter-inch product, however, is apparently not easy to get right now, so one of the bids used half-inch instead, doubling the materials cost for that component.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, the incredible demand that still exists for contractors and people in the construction industry. It’s likely some of the prices are so high simply to make the market clear. If you want to do a project now, it will not be cheap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, my impression is that we slightly underestimated the overheads involved in working in my neighborhood. Parking is scarce, and it’s a multi-family building (with all the concomitant rules and regulations), not a single-family suburban home with easy access and few restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What to do, then?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Either way, I’m resigned to spending more than I had planned to. Fortunately, I’m in a position to do that, so it shouldn’t be a big problem. The more vexed question is exactly how much more to spend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://st.hzcdn.com/simgs/pictures/salles-de-bain/abbeville-terre-grise-img~97715fc70daf124b_14-5849-1-7529adc.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A bathroom&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Sadly, I don't have this much space. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.houzz.fr/photos/abbeville-phvw-vp~150420990&quot;&gt;Photo&lt;/a&gt; courtesy &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.houzz.fr/pro/webuser-574038528/terre-grise&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Terre Grise&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current thought is to wait, hoping the demand for contractors cools down a bit, and expand the scope to spread out the project overheads a bit more. I had planned to eventually redo the bathroom and add more storage eventually, why not do it now? Especially if I have to spend so much more anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m still waiting on meta-estimates from the contractors on demand trends heading into next year. If they see it tapering off, that might be one indication to wait. And then, if I wind up doing the additional projects, it’s back to the drawing board with my architects to design a bathroom!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I’m going to have to start spending about $100 every month to keep my cabinets — which have made it to the US from Denmark — in storage somewhere in New Jersey.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 04 Sep 2021 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/crossroads</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/crossroads</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>