<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Renovation Diary</title>
        <description>Joseph renovates his kitchen.</description>
        <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/</link>
        <atom:link href="https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2023 10:20:32 -0600</pubDate>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2023 10:20:32 -0600</lastBuildDate>
        <generator>Jekyll v4.0.1</generator>
        
            <item>
                <title>Waiting for Final Details</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been a while, and to be honest, there hasn’t been that much happening. There are a few small details where they’ve made progress. But for the most part, I’m still waiting for the last details to happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of progress,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/oven-drawer.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Oven moved&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The oven is now in the correct location above the drawer&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2023 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/waiting-for-details</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/waiting-for-details</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Inching Toward Completion</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;There was a bit of activity on site yesterday as the carpenters returned to make progress on millwork installation. They got most of the panels mostly installed, and they made some progress fixing other issues like the appliance installation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the appliances, the oven shelf got installed, so my oven is now correctly installed above the lower drawer. Unfortunately, the power receptacle for the oven is too big. The electricians will have to come back and make some adjustments to the oven can be pushed all the way back into the cabinet box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/oven-drawer.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Oven moved&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The oven is now in the correct location above the drawer&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, my refrigerator installation got closer, but still isn’t quite there. They flipped the door, so it’s now hinged on the left. This makes a lot more sense trying to get out ingredients from the kitchen area on the right of it. It’s also now firmly anchored in the cabinet box. That said, I have some concerns: the top filler piece still isn’t installed correctly, and the front of the appliance isn’t plumb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/panels-nearly.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Panels installed&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Ignore the mess: the panels are now mostly and mostly correctly installed, the last big messy job&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest and messiest job got close as well: the carpenter got most of the mega pegboard panels mostly installed. It looks very slick, and it will look even better once the former kitchen area gets tidied up. Of course, nothing on this project is without caveats. One of the panels was installed the wrong way around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confusion more generally resulted in having to sacrifice a couple of panels. Good planning meant there’s an extra sheet they can use to re-make the missing pieces. Those will get CNC milled to the exact size required, and should slot in later without too much fuss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow I’m finally getting all my furniture back in. Though there are still myriad additional punch list items that need to get done, however. Probably most acutely in my eyes: handles for all my cabinets and getting the cabinet panel installed on my dishwasher. It’s very difficult to load when you have to hold the door down with one arm or your leg.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/inching</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/inching</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Corian, Part IV</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Progress in the week after the big push has been slower. The countertop team did make a fourth and I hope final appearance. As far as I can tell, they’re truly done. It looks good, and it’s very gratifying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The waterfall piece on the side of the oven cabinet was the last major component to go in. It was a bit tricky, requiring them to sand off a finished edge and seam the side piece to the main body of the countertop. The end result looks pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/waterfall.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Waterfall countertop&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The last major piece to install was a waterfall on the side of the oven cabinet&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were a few other small parts to finish up too. They buffed out a few nicks the electricians left behind and did some sealing to prevent water from getting to vulnerable wood surfaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project is tantalizingly close to done. It’s almost more painful the closer it gets to being finished. The biggest project still to do is the installation of the wood panels in the former kitchen area. I’m really hoping that does happen this week: once that’s been taken care of, I think I’m in good shape to have all my furniture moved back from storage. I’ll finally have my home back, even if there are still a few assorted punch list items left to do.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2022 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/corian-iv</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/corian-iv</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Just About Functional</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;With an almighty push, I was able to get a working kitchen by Thanksgiving. All the major appliances are working, and I’ve got a working kitchen sink again. That’s a huge relief. But there’s also a lot left to do, and I’m not quite ready to call in the movers to bring back my furniture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The electricians were on site and got a lot done. They finally connected up all the circuits and installed most of my appliances. I now have working switched lights in my living room again, a working cooktop and oven, a mostly working refrigerator, and circuits for everything from my vent hood to garbage disposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/cooktop-installed.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cooktop&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The cooktop sits flush with the countertop&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plumbers got all the final plumbing work done by my reckoning. There wasn’t all that much to do, though it was pretty critical. The water to my kitchen has been turned back on, and my kitchen sink has both a working faucet and drain plus garbage disposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also made the plumbing connections for my new dishwasher. Of course, my insistence on having a disguised dishwasher means that it isn’t completely functional. While it has power and water, the carpenter hasn’t been back to install the cabinet panel — essential for making the door easy to open — and it’s not installed into the adjoining cabinets, since that needs to be very precise, to ensure the door lines up with the other cabinets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But: I can cook, clean, and store food now, so I can cook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s definitely going to get some getting used to. The fan assist in my new oven is so much more effective than my old one, I’m having to adjust my baking times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking ahead, there’s one big project left to do: get the cabinet panels in the old kitchen installed. There’s also a bevy of smaller items that do need to be done for the project to be completely wrapped up. That’s everything form installing the cabinet door handles to making sure my refrigerator is actually installed correctly into the cabinet box.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2022 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/functional</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/functional</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Corian, Part III</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;With Thanksgiving fast approaching, I’ve been really pushing to get the project to the point that I could at least cook dinner Thursday. The solid surface installers were on site again Monday to continue progress on the Corian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Friday they wrapped up most of the backsplash pieces. On Monday, they continued with a return piece to cover the side of the wall opening, as well as (almost) all the pieces to clad the upper cabinet boxes. It’s an interesting sight to see the pieces compressed into place temporarily while the adhesive cures. They weigh a ton, so it’s not surprising they need some initial support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/counters-upper-close.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Corian being supported&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Bracing has been installed to support the Corian while the adhesive cures&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They still have a few more pieces to do. There’s a tiny piece that needs to go in on the underside of the cabinets, and another piece that goes on the side of the oven cabinet to cover that cabinet box and complete the look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, there’s supposed to be quite a bit of activity. The plumber and electrician should be on site to install appliances and the plumbing fixtures. The carpenter is supposed to be back to get the rest of the millwork installed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/corian-iii</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/corian-iii</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Corian, Part II</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;I take the progress I can get. The solid surface team returned yesterday to continue working on the Corian installation. They definitely moved the project forward — more on that in a bit — though didn’t quite get the installation done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course of this project never did run smooth. There was some confusion around the space that would be left underneath the cabinets for the strip of LED lighting and power outlets. Those will get hidden in a small gap between the bottom of the cabinet boxes and the backsplash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/counters-backsplash-corner.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Backsplash&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The backsplash has gone in successfully&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, it was possible to swap out the half-inch wallboard with quarter-inch wallboard to compensate for the fact they’ve had to use half-inch (rather than quarter-inch) Corian on the backsplash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/counters-channel.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Channel&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;A strip of LED lights and a run of outlets will get installed in this gap&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that detail in place, they were able to successfully install the backsplash pieces behind the cooktop and on the side wall with the lighting controls. It looks very sharp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also drilled out the hole for the sink faucet. I was a bit overeager and roughly installed the faucet (which has been sitting, waiting, in my apartment for months) to see what it looks like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/counters-faucet-temporary.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Faucet mock up&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;I couldn't help myself and slipped the faucet in to see what it would look like. Sadly, the plumbing isn't connected up.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, the solid surface installers weren’t quite able to finish by the time my building’s approved construction hours ran out. They’ve still got to install pieces to clad the underside of the upper cabinets, a piece on the side of the upper cabinet run, and a small piece to cover the currently exposed side of the oven cabinet at the end of the base cabinet run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Thanksgiving rapidly approaching next week, I’m really hoping they can get enough done in the working days next week that I can have a working kitchen again. Given how this effort has gone, I think truly finishing the project is probably unrealistic. But if I could have a working refrigerator, a bit of lighting, water, and my appliances working, that would be pretty amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2022 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/corian-ii</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/corian-ii</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Countertop Installation Begins</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;With painful slowness, there has been a tiny bit of additional progress. The solid surface installers were here yesterday and made a good start getting all the Corian installed. That will make up the worktops themselves, and also clad surfaces like the backsplash and underside of the upper cabinets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s another one of those steps that’s gratifying in that the kitchen is finally beginning to feel complete. In theory, there really are only a few more days of work to go. Seeing the sink properly in place is really encouraging: I’m hoping I could have working plumbing again very soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/counters-wide.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Counter installed&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The Corian over the base cabinets has gone in&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as seems to be the theme on this project, this step has not been without its challenges. The solid surface team had to demount the panels that started going up last Thursday in what was the kitchen. There were concerns with their installation anyway, so perhaps it’s not a huge loss. It’s hard not to feel the step backwards: something finished now looks incomplete again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also hit snags with some of the other details on the Corian install, which meant they weren’t able to get beyond the sheets over the base cabinets. There’s still a lot to do: the backsplash, waterfall pieces along the un-clad cabinet boxes, and the exposed sides of the upper cabinets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/counters-sag.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sagging cabinet box&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;I'm not totally sure what happened here in the cabinet box that holds the sink, but it doesn't look great&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few weird details that made me raise my eyebrows as well. There’s a worrying amount of sag in the fronts of the cabinet boxes that will support the new cooktop and sink. And I’ve found a few more places where my beautiful new floor has been dinged in probably irreversible ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s hoping they’re able to continue the momentum and get the bulk of the major steps done this week.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2022 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/corian</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/corian</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Panel Installation</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;The project continues to inch toward the finish line. Yesterday, they began installing the wood panels in what was the kitchen area. It’s a surprisingly delicate and complicated ballet of pieces that need to line up due to the perforations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, they had to install the floating steel shelves. Having lugged two of them up from the basement when they were delivered, they are astonishingly heavy. Installed, they have that fun feeling of defying gravity. I’m a little less excited about the fact they cut holes in the newly finished and painted wall to fit them in. That’s not going to be a fun patch job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/panels-opening.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Through the opening&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Looking through the kitchen wall, it's a bit easier to see the floating steel shelves&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The panels themselves aren’t quite done. But they made a ton of progress, and it’s beginning to look good. Once again, I find myself in the interesting position where I take photos and it looks so like the renders that I looked at almost two years ago in the design phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/panels-detail.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Panel detail&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The thick flying wall that backs the kitchen cabinets will get an end cap mirror to add light and a feeling of space&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what I’ve been told, they won’t be back until Monday to finish the panels. The other big blocker is the solid surface cladding that will form the countertops, backsplash, and caps around the upper cabinets. Once that’s in, the plumbing and electrical get get wrapped up, as the sink, faucet, and appliances all interface with those pieces in some way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2022 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/panels</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/panels</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Painting, Part III</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;The painters made another trip and wrapped up their work. It’s nice to be another step closer to having my home back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the vast quantity of home renovation media teaches us anything, it’s that an image or video conceals many sins when it comes to painting. Which is to say, I found it difficult to convey the sense of progress the painting has given when you’re on the site in person. It feels a lot more finished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/painting-hall-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Looking down the hall&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;All the marigold paint is now gone&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most visibly, all the ceiling scars have been patched, sanded, and painted. I’m trying not to get too hung up on the details: it looks a lot better now. Without knowing where the old walls came down, I doubt anyone could point to where the patches have been done. The fresh coat of paint on the ceiling makes a surprisingly big difference, as I may have noted earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/ceiling-patched.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ceiling&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Virtually impossible to tell where the ceiling damage was&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crew also patched a hole in the bathroom wall, painted the new baseboard in my bedroom, and fixed my error with a coat of flat paint over the eggshell. It’s still drying, so it doesn’t have the delicious velvety feel quite yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m really hoping the contractor can keep this momentum up. Aside from the punch list, we’re down to only a few major jobs. They need to install the CNC panels in the old kitchen space, which gets most of the remaining material off the floor. All the Corian needs to be installed. Once that’s done, they can finish the plumbing and electric, and I think we’re close to done.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2022 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/painting-iii</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/painting-iii</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Painting, Part II</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;The painters have been back and continue to make progress. I made one small mistake that hopefully isn’t too hard to remediate. Most dramatically, they’ve gotten the plywood ready for the millwork installation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My error was one of omission. A few years ago I repainted most of my apartment myself over a few weekends. After much debate, I used Farrow and Ball “Strong White,” which I thought struck a nice balance between coolness and intensity. (My initial idea to use their “All White” was very instructive. The intensity of that nearly seared my retinas.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than have the painters start from scratch, I figured it would be easiest to repaint in the same color. But I failed to mention that I wanted Farrow and Ball’s flat finish paint, rather than eggshell. I’m hoping they need to come back for a second coat after sanding, and can correct this without too much of a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The repairs to wall and ceiling damage continues as well. It’s looking good. While they still have more work to do, it’s a lot better than it was. In a few places, aside from the fact it hasn’t been painted yet, all the construction scars are completely gone now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/painting-black.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Plywood painted black&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The two panel walls got a coat of black paint before the panels get attached&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In anticipation of the millwork installation next week, the plywood panels have gotten their coat of black paint. It’s made the old kitchen space a lot more dramatic. Fortunately it won’t be quite as dark once the millwork goes in on top. Though I do kind of like the look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next week I’m hoping they can finish the painting, get the millwork installed, and, if they can get the countertops installed too, the project may actually get wrapped up. Or at the very least, I may have a working kitchen again.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/painting-ii</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145/painting-ii</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>