<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Renovation Diary</title>
        <description>Joseph renovates his kitchen.</description>
        <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145//kitchen145/</link>
        <atom:link href="https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145//kitchen145/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 Mar 2021 15:10:46 -0600</pubDate>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Mar 2021 15:10:46 -0600</lastBuildDate>
        <generator>Jekyll v4.0.1</generator>
        
            <item>
                <title>Before the Bids</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;More developments are afoot! The cabinet order is in, as mentioned last time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of the cabinet order itself, once it was ready to go, the process was pretty painless. The total bill came to $11,509. That doesn’t include all the cabinet boxes: the laundry, refrigerator, and upper cabinet boxes will be custom. But it does include additional paneling for the new entry-office area that will be created in the current kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/pegboard-final.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A refined version of the former kitchen area. The panels being ordered from Reform will make up the pegboard system. (Image credit: BOS|UA )&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next week or two I really will go look at flooring, and start figuring out how to get all my appliances here on time.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Thu, 04 Mar 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145//kitchen145/about-to-bid</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145//kitchen145/about-to-bid</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Cabinets, Part V</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Finally, the cabinets are ordered. But the pandemic strikes again: the final delivery window is 14 to 18 weeks. I’m hoping it will be possible to get the work started sooner. There’s a lot of demolition and construction that needs to happen before the cabinets go in. Then again, from what I hear, it may also be difficult to book a contractor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of the cabinet order itself, once it was ready to go, the process was pretty painless. The total bill came to $11,509. That doesn’t include all the cabinet boxes: the laundry, refrigerator, and upper cabinet boxes will be custom. But it does include additional paneling for the new entry-office area that will be created in the current kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/pegboard-final.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A refined version of the former kitchen area. The panels being ordered from Reform will make up the pegboard system. (Image credit: BOS|UA )&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next week or two I really will go look at flooring, and start figuring out how to get all my appliances here on time.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145//kitchen145/cabinets-part-v</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145//kitchen145/cabinets-part-v</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Cabinets, Part IV</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Getting a final specification for the cabinets has been quite a journey. Never would I have guessed it would be so difficult to do something as simple as pick out how to arrange drawers. But after several weeks — plus a break for Christmas and New Year — I have a final layout, down to which drawers go where. There’s also been some interesting back and forth about what to do behind the new kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting with the cabinet layout, once I had finalized appliances and the general layout I had to get into detail. In particular figuring out how I wanted to arrange the lower cabinets. From the beginning, I’ve been pretty certain that I wanted drawers in the lower cabinets rather than doors with shelves inside. Once you’ve used a kitchen like this, you’ll never go back. I also wanted pull-outs with interior drawers. In some ways it’s a bit more inconvenient, but it looks a bit more streamlined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/basis-pullout.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Reform Basis with full-height interior pullout.&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;An example of a full-height pull-out in a different Reform option. (Photo credit: Reform)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My initial choices for interior drawers turned out not to work. I had too many drawers and the wrong choices for inserts. After much back and forth, I managed to find something that did work. I’m going with Blum’s Legrabox line of drawer boxes that has a corresponding set of organizing inserts, which should be nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/drawer-layout.png&quot; alt=&quot;Drawer layout diagram&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;My near-final attempt at coming up with a workable drawer layout for the lower cabinets.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, someone then realized that even that plan wouldn’t work. Because I’m getting the world’s fanciest German induction cooktop, there wasn’t going to be enough space to stack the oven below the cooktop. One option would’ve been to build out a super-thick worktop, to add height for the cooktop to have enough clearance over the oven. The second — what I went for — was an unexpected windfall, even if there was a slight aesthetic compromise, in the feature image at the top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/legrabox.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Blum's Legrabox system&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Blum's Legrabox drawer system. (Image credit: Blum)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to admit, the oven sitting on the right like that does look a little awkward. But there are advantages, too. I feel a lot better — given how small the space is — with an international-style 60 cm oven. I’m never going to host 30 people for Thanksgiving here. There isn’t enough space! Having a smaller oven should reduce my energy footprint. Plus, because it’s also a bit shorter than a 30” wall oven, I get a cool drawer under the oven for baking equipment. By sticking storage under the cooktop, I get that extra six inches of space, even if I can’t have a top drawer because of the cooktop’s height. It’s also a happy accident that the smaller oven is about $2,000 cheaper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cabinet order still hasn’t gone in. Because of our super fun pandemic, the delivery time has slipped to up to 18 weeks. The final price tag clocks in at about $9,500, though that includes some paneling for the area behind the newly relocated kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of, there’s been much more interesting back and forth over the newly created space in the soon-to-be former kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not exactly sure what to call the space. Maybe I’ve been watching &lt;em&gt;Grand Designs&lt;/em&gt; for too long, but I like to think of it as a mini-snug. The idea for now is to stash my piano there, thus freeing up the main living space to compensate for the intrusion of the kitchen there. It’s also a nice opportunity to make the entry to my apartment nicer. As it currently stands, coming inside is very awkward. The door sits at an angle to the walls on either side, and with such a narrow space it almost feels like you’re walking into the wall when you enter. Plus, there isn’t any storage for coats, bags, or shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/final-floorplan.png&quot; alt=&quot;Final floorplan&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The final floorplan. (Image credit: BOS | UA)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the awkwardness is resolved by tearing out the wall, so there’s ample space when you walk in the door. The storage was a bit more fun to work through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first concept was what I christened the “luxe Japanese mudroom.” It envisioned wood cladding, lots of upper storage, and what amounted to an open closet. There were a lot of great ideas. It looked very luxe and very sleek without being cold. The architects suggested using Corian for the backing and shoe shelf, which would’ve been very easy to clean. Unfortunately, I don’t have a palatial apartment where it might make sense to devote 70 square feet to an entry vestibule. Even in the render, my piano looks a little bit strange sitting in what’s effectively a closet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/entry-concept-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Initial entry concept&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The luxe Japanese mudroom concept. (Image credit: BOS | UA)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it was back to the drawing board. I suggested the Opencase system from Henrybuilt, which, while very cool, at around $10,000 for the set I wanted, was a bit outside the budget for this project. My architects came up with a very cool design that echoed that, with a pegboard system potentially wrapping two walls and into the kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really love this concept. It adds a bit of whimsy, still ties together with the kitchen — the pegboard will be made from the same material as the kitchen fronts — and gives very flexible storage. It also helps resolve my slight concern over the omission of one wall cabinet in the kitchen area, which my architects thought avoided an awkward joint at the refrigerator. I bought the argument enough to go along, but it was a little sad to give up some precious storage in a space so small. Potentially adding the peg system in the kitchen should make it possible to reclaim that as storage space, if perhaps in a way that cants more towards style than function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/pegboard-initial.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Initial pegboard entry concept&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The initial pegboard concept. (Image credit: BOS | UA)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next few weeks, the project should really get going. Or at least I suspect I’ll feel that way because I’ll have to start spending serious money. The cabinet order should go in soon, and I’m already looking at ordering the appliances to avoid delays that may exist because of the pandemic’s continued impact. I’ll probably also start getting a sense of the construction costs as we begin looking at contractors to execute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next time, there should be more details on the very cool pegboard system, and I’m planning a bit of a “staycation” to visit design showrooms. I need to pick out new flooring and begin to look at materials for the worktops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Feature image credit BOS |UA&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145//kitchen145/cabinets-part-iv</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145//kitchen145/cabinets-part-iv</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Cabinets, Part III</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Before spending upwards of $10,000 on something, it’s worth taking the time to see what you’re buying in person. Or at least to the extent possible in current circumstances. If it were easier to travel, I probably would have made a trip down to New York to look at complete kitchens made with Reform’s cabinet system. I’ve chosen to settle for more pandemic-friendly samples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The leading contender was Reform’s “Frame” option in white. Fortunately they had that option in stock as a sample, so I was able to get my hands on that. My architects are also big fans of natural wood, so they also pulled the “Basis” option in oak veneer for me to look at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/basis-on-white.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Basis&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The Reform Basis option. I liked the oak look more than I would've guessed. I was not as thrilled with the built-in handle.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was pleasantly surprised with the oak veneer finish. My inclination is against lots and lots of natural wood. I couldn’t articulate exactly why. But the oak is really quite nice. Certainly much nicer than other oak effect or oak veneers I’ve seen in fancy hotel rooms or other people’s less “designed” kitchens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was unpleasantly disappointed by the integrated circular cutout handle. I love the idea of a kitchen without pulls. It’s sleeker, more compact, and presents fewer chances to catch stuff (like a headphone cable or coat). But the integrated pulls on the Basis didn’t float my boat. They’re small and a little uncomfortable. There also wasn’t a ton of attention paid to the feeling of the surface you touch. It feels like bland just-sanded-enough wood. There is no joy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks kind of cool. I could see this being a good option for something other than a kitchen that’s opened less often. Having to deal with that built-in pull every day would drive me crazy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/frame-with-book.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Frame&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The Reform Frame in white. This is positioned roughly where the new run of kitchen cabinets will sit. My apartment faces north, so everything is washed in a very painterly soft light.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At any rate, I was already much more inclined to the Frame look painted white. After living with the samples for a few days, I’ve more or less committed to it. It has the whiff of classicism that I like with a bit of a modern twist. Rather than a bog standard shaker look, it evokes it with an edgy angled frame. There’s texture as the wood grain shows through the paint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/frame-white-on-white.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Frame with quartz&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Experimenting with worktop options against an end table with a marble-effect quartz composite.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m still waiting on final pricing for the cabinets. I also need to figure out exactly how I want the drawers and doors configured. Once that’s all set, the order can go in, and the fun really begins. With a provisional delivery date, I can start the planning process (getting approval from my condo board) and pick a contractor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Feature image credit BOS |UA&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 13 Dec 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145//kitchen145/cabinets-part-iii</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145//kitchen145/cabinets-part-iii</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Cabinets, Part II</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;The cabinet saga continues. It’s turning out to be a surprisingly fraught question. Perhaps that makes sense given it is the biggest single expense in the whole project. On the other hand, lots of other very expensive choices were easy, be that the layout or my prospective fancy German appliances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last time, I had gotten some preliminary estimates on cabinet prices, and all but ruled out “the Germans:” Bulthaup, Poggenpohl, Leicht, SieMatic. I was still waiting on firmer pricing from them, as well as pricing from a few more options. I’ll get into where I’m thinking in a moment. First, I want to do a bit of public service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/reform-frame.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Reform Frame&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Reform's Frame series in white (Image credit: Reform)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back when I was doing this project on my own, I found it somewhat maddening that none of the really high-end cabinet companies gave even a hint of what their prices were online or even when I went to visit a showroom in a couple of cases. So I’m going to quickly list out some of the prices that my architects pulled for this project. I’m hoping that Google indexes this page, and then the next time someone types “SieMatic pricing” into Google, they might get this page and find something that’s actually informative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Manufacturer&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Details&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Price&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Poggenpohl&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Segmento series&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;At least $50,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bulthaup&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Standard wood veneer, counters, backsplash, sink, faucet included&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$55,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;SieMatic&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Pure collection “Similaque” with laminated door edges, lighting included&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$37,200&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Leicht&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Topos wood veneer, lighting, tax, shipping, delivery included&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$37,200&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Leicht&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Fenix NTM doors, lighting, tax, shipping, delivery included&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$28,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Leicht&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Laminate doors, lighting, tax, shipping, delivery included&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$25,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Space Theory&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Laminate or natural wood veneer doors&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$22,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Custom Cabinets&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Painted wood doors&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$15,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reform&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Up with Ikea boxes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$10,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reform&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Frame with Ikea boxes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$10,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reform&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Degree with Ikea boxes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$7,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reform&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Basis with Ikea boxes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$5,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve left out the option I’m probably going to choose — Reform cabinet boxes with Reform fronts — because I’m still not sure the pricing on that option is exactly right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of, as these prices suggest, I’m not going to be getting my cabinets from one of the German brands. To keep to my overall $40,000 budget, the cabinets need to sit somewhere around $10,0000, and even the cheapest option from Leicht is more than twice that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that I’ve seen some samples of the Reform options (at this point only in photos, but hopefully in the flesh soon!), and they’re quite nice. In my mind, the biggest disadvantage of their system relative to the more expensive ones is flexibility: they can’t make boxes in totally custom sizes to use up every last inch of space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/ikea.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Ikea cabinet displays&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Ikea's cabinet boxes on display with transparent fronts to show off the hardware. They're using white-label Blum Tandembox, which, while nice, is not as good as the Blum Legrabox system.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the plus side, the Reform first-party cabinet boxes use Blum’s top-of-the-line Legrabox drawer system, the same set of drawer runners that all the really high-end companies use. The only real sacrifice there is a few millimeters here and there: Poggenpohl uses their own drawer boxes that are 8 mm thick rather than the Blum Legrabox system at a comparatively gigantic 12 mm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/november-white.png&quot; alt=&quot;The current concept in white&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The current layout thought in white. They've added in my real appliances (at least the ones that will be visible) and some touches like the idea of adding an uplight rather than a second level of upper cabinets. (Image credit: BOS|UA)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choice of cabinets will also guide a lot of the timing. Assuming I go with one of the Reform options, that will take about 3-4 months to manufacture and ship over from Denmark. The idea, then, is to iron out the remaining details as part of the design, find a contractor, get approvals, and then begin work so that when the cabinets arrive everything is ready for them to go in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My architects seem to think that a wood finish would look good. I’m leaning more towards something in a solid color. I don’t know that I have any sort of principled argument, other than I find a solid color more to my taste. I’m also slightly reneging on my appliance choices: after giving it some thought, I think I want a 30” cooktop after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/november-wood.png&quot; alt=&quot;The current concept in oak&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The same as above, but in an oak veneer rather than a painted finish. (Image credit: BOS|UA)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that’s all still up in the air. I’m hoping within the next few weeks I can have all the basic layout and cabinet choices made so this can really get going. Much as I don’t love the idea of living with dust everywhere, the road to a better kitchen will have to begin with a little bit of demolition.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 28 Nov 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145//kitchen145/cabients-part-ii</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145//kitchen145/cabients-part-ii</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Cabinets Are Expensive</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;When we left off, I had been asked to choose a layout. There was the more conservative option — leaving the kitchen in place and slightly reorganizing — versus the bolder option of creating an office with a linear kitchen in my living room. After some consideration, I decided to go down the linear kitchen route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The area where the new cabinets go is already dead space: I can’t put anything there because it would block access to the rest of my apartment and the kitchen. If I can fill that in, and also get a small room for a desk or my piano, that seems like a great idea. It also made a lot more sense when I realized it was possible to get rid of the island-cum-dining table. I should probably get a smaller dining table at some point, but in any case, that’s much more flexible when it’s not fixed as a set of cabinets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of which, the next choice I have to make is where to get the cabinets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cabinet choice is perhaps the most vexed question of the whole project. I’m pretty adamant about getting nice appliances, so I’m taking as a given that I’ll spend more there than most people would. Construction is more or less a fixed cost: either the plumbing is successfully configured or it’s not. As far as I’m aware, there’s no “luxury plumbing” I could buy to go in the walls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/option3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Kitchen Render&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The prospective reconfiguration. (Image credit: BOS|UA)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If money were no object, I’d get cabinets from one of the high-end German manufacturers. But it wasn’t clear exactly how much these companies charged for their products. When I went to visit places like Poggenpohl and SieMatic in the pre-architect days, they more or less refused to give me prices without fairly detailed architectural drawings. It seemed within the realm of possibility that — especially since it’s such a small kitchen — I might be able to squeeze a fancy German kitchen into my big-but-not-really-that-big roughly $40,000 budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rough estimates that my architects got were surprising. Some were more than I would’ve imagined. Others were still outside my budget, but a lot more reasonable than I would’ve guessed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two most expensive were Bulthaup — at a whopping $55,000 — and Poggenpohl. Money aside, Poggenpohl was my top pick. They are so expensive that projects have a hard floor of $50,000, and it’s hard to imagine that I’d want to get the absolute cheapest, most basic option they offer. They’re so expensive the Poggenpohl team didn’t even want to see the drawings to contemplate giving a more affordable bid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second choice, SieMatic, came in lower than I would’ve guessed, at around $25,000. My architects also looked at Leicht, which came in around the same price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/siematic-pure-010.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;SieMatic Pure&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;A SieMatic Kitchen I can't afford. (Image credit: SieMatic)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zooming out a little, the cabinets more or less need to cost about $10,000. With my $40,000 budget, about $10,000 will go to appliances, and the architects are working with a $10,000 figure for all the construction costs, like moving the plumbing and moving walls. With $10,000 spent on cabinets, that leaves a further $10,000 for other finishes like worktops and lighting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus: the final option on the table is the “IKEA hack.” In particular, my architects have proposed going with Reform, a company out of Copenhagen that offers “designer” fronts for IKEA cabinet shells. That looks like it will fall somewhere closer to $7500 for the options that looked the most promising to me. I should get a quote from Space Theory in the next few days as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/fold.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Reform Degree&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Reform's Degree design. (Image credit: Reform)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a way, I find this comforting. I worry that I’m spending way, way too much money on fancy appliances. But even if I go down to more “conventional” choices for my oven or refrigerator, I still wouldn’t be able to afford one of my fancy German cabinet options. It seems possible I might even get the project in under $40,000, which could leave some latitude for buying some extra fancy lighting or laundry appliances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I have this narrowed down a bit, there will be more renders to finalize the design, and then it comes down to scheduling. Finding a contractor will depend a lot on the point at which I can take delivery of the cabinets at the core of the design.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145//kitchen145/cabients-are-expensive</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145//kitchen145/cabients-are-expensive</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Step One</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;While signing up with an architect is a big step, I don’t think the project will feel completely real until I start signing the really big checks and the construction team starts to set up camp in my living room. Even so, it’s getting interesting. I had the first formal meeting with the architects after signing the paperwork, and we have some preliminary options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next few weeks should see us achieve a few key milestones in terms of the schedule. Most importantly, I need to choose a layout, which drives most of the other decisions on the project. I’ve also been asked to start assembling a list of appliances, fixtures, and fittings so we can begin to price everything out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the appliance end of things, I have a head start. I bought a swanky Miele dishwasher — they really are the best — a couple of years ago, which will be reinstalled in the new kitchen. Given my excellent experience with Miele products over the years, I’d love to outfit the whole kitchen with their stuff. It’s slightly complicated by the fact they sell only a small, less up-to-date line of products in the US, and the models they do have here are exceptionally pricey. I’ll have to see how other parts of the budget shake out. I am very tempted to spring for the Miele cooktop anyway. It’s the only one I’ve been able to find that can bridge all the power together to send 7700 W to a single pan. It might actually be possible to do great stir fry at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/dishwashers.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dishwashers&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Shopping for dishwashers in a more innocent time at Yale Appliance.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of the slightly more consequential decision about the layout, the architects have proposed a couple of different layout concepts. First, the more straightforward option maintains essentially the same layout, but opens the space up and makes it a bit more sociable. On the downside, it doesn’t really create all that much more space to work in, and it would be possibly even more of a squeeze to fit multiple people in the kitchen at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an aside, this exercise has really brought home the fact I could use more space, full stop. And while the real estate agent that helped me buy this apartment told me to start planning for “phase II” when I signed the offer letter, I don’t think that’s in the cards anytime soon. It’s slightly horrifying to think for the money I’m spending to completely redo my kitchen, I could only buy about 25 more square feet of space in this neighborhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/conservative.png&quot; alt=&quot;Safe option&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The more conservative option: this keeps my services in more or less the same place but rearranges to make things more open and create more work space. (Image credit: BOS|UA)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second more interesting option I can’t quite make my mind up on. It’s definitely bold. In this world, what’s now the kitchen becomes (at least in this version) an office. The kitchen then rather voraciously gobbles up the living room and a closet to span over 15 feet, plus a mini-island.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/bold.png&quot; alt=&quot;Interesting option&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The more inventive option: in this world, the kitchen spreads its wings. I get a big long linear run of cabinets at the cost of a closet, and a mini extra room for something where the kitchen sits now. (Image credit: BOS|UA)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love the extra space for cooking, of course. I’m less sure I want the kitchen to take over quite so much, however well the ultimate design manages to blur the kitchen into the background and turn it into furniture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve wondered whether the putative office couldn’t become something other than an office. While working in my bedroom is maybe not ideal, I’ve settled into a nice rhythm. Whereas, if it could be made to feel less closed off, it might be fun to turn the former kitchen into a “music room”, so that the living space doesn’t feel quite as cramped if the kitchen gets so moved around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doubtless, there will be some further revisions. I’m not sure how often I’ll update this as those move along, but at the very least there will be another post in a few weeks when the layout and some other final decisions are made. It’s becoming real! As long as the budget doesn’t completely fall apart — and perhaps skirting over the whole my-home-will-be-a-construction-site issue — this should be fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Feature image credit: BOS|UA&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145//kitchen145/step-one</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145//kitchen145/step-one</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Finding an Architect</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve crossed the Rubicon. On Friday, I signed the paperwork to engage an architectural practice and get the project underway. I’ll have more to share about what I’m doing later once the actual design and build processes get underway. For now, I’ll walk through the mechanics of even finding an architect to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the beginning, I’ve wanted to hire an architect. But it wasn’t entirely clear whether my project was big enough to justify hiring one. Obviously if you’re building a house, you’ll need an architect. If the project is really small — replacing a bathroom vanity or installing built-in bookcases — you probably don’t need an architect. Others advised me that an architect would add to the project cost, and that a good design-build contractor could deal with my changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I found a credible contractor, though, it became clear I needed an architect in at least some capacity. Their stated reason had something to do with regulations governing fire suppression systems. There’s a fire sprinkler in my kitchen, and it’s possible it may need to be moved. That, apparently, requires a registered architect to sign off on the plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between my ambivalence about the contractor to begin with and the supposed requirement, when I decided to dust this project off around a month ago I decided I would at least explore the idea of hiring an architect. If they told me my project was too small, at least I’d know that I had made the right choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding an architect, though, proved to be harder than I would’ve guessed. Most of the obvious resources like Houzz were unhelpful in that the sort order of firms tended to correlate with the size or “prestige” of the practice, and there weren’t a lot of other levers to find what I was looking for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether it’s being in New England or being in the US more generally, most firms seem to cater to people who want something either very cookie cutter or very showy. There are lots of photos of double-wide Wolf ranges that cost more than some compact cars and other touches that look generically expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://st.hzcdn.com/simgs/pictures/kitchens/kitchen-krieger-associates-architects-inc-img~ad81ab970f7c97cc_9-4138-1-8234192.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;No thanks kitchen image&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;A cookie-cutter high-end suburban kitchen. At least this one looks well-executed, even if the design is a little tired. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.houzz.fr/photos/kitchen-phvw-vp~771539&quot;&gt;Photo&lt;/a&gt; courtesy &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.houzz.fr/hznb/professionnels/architecte/krieger-associates-architects-inc-pfvwus-pf~1702898409&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Krieger + Associates Architects, Inc.&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are places like Architizer or even Instagram. But the listing sites don’t tend to be comprehensive — the practice I hired isn’t on Architizer, for example — and Instagram is hard to browse if you’re looking for more than “inspiration.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, I found a firm through a combination of meticulousness and good luck. The initial shortlist of firms came from literally clicking on close to 100 firms’ listings on Houzz and though more straightforward Web searches. From there, a few never wrote back to my emails, and a few set up initial consultations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite what I would’ve guessed, a lot of firms have such a backlog of work that at least a few couldn’t have fit me in until the next year. Fortunately, the director of one practice was able to refer me to &lt;a href=&quot;https://bos-ua.com/about/&quot;&gt;BOS|UA&lt;/a&gt;, who (most importantly) really impressed me, and had enough capacity to start my small project immediately to boot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every practice I talked to made me feel pretty confident that hiring an architect was the right choice. Even the fanciest-looking practices that listed very big, very expensive projects on their websites seemed very down to earth and willing to take on my project. They all, even in my brief consultations, had ideas that never would have crossed my mind. The architects at the practice I wound up hiring suggested, for instance, that there were a few ways I might avoid moving my electrical panel. Avoiding that one change alone probably covers the cost of hiring them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of which, I have since discovered that architects’ fees typically run about 10-15% of the construction cost. In other words, for a $50,000 project, the architects’ fees would run round $5,000 to $7,500. Some will literally charge a fraction of the construction bill. Others — including all the firms that made my shortlist, which was not intentional but probably not a coincidence — bill either hourly or with fixed fees. As one person put it to me, there really isn’t a lot more work involved for the architects if I happen to want a really expensive refrigerator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the initial consultation, the architects sent over a formal proposal. Basically, a contract about the work, including a rough schedule, pricing, and each side’s obligations. Signing that document on Friday is what kicked off this whole process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All-in, I’ll be spending about $4500 in architects’ fees, which works out to something like 15% of my (very provisional) $30,000 construction budget. There’s some variability in the cost of the construction administration phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fee structure breaks down roughly equally through the different major design phases. The first chunk to establish the current site conditions, the second to build a rough schematic design, the third to develop more detailed drawings for regulatory approval, and fourth the final detailed drawings and final budget tweaks. That comes to about $4,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there, I’ve chosen to spend the extra money — billed hourly — to have the architects manage the team of contractors actually doing the construction. On the surface it seems like a slightly absurd level of bureaucracy for such a small project: I manage the architects who manage the general contractor who manages the actual workers. But even my brief interactions with general contractors have convinced me this will probably be worth the money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll have more to say on the project design in a few weeks. They’re working away: my first design meeting happens at the end of the month. For now, I’ve been asked to put together a mood board (the headline image) to give the architects an idea of what I want. I’m also beginning to think about cash flow, the true limits of what I’m going to spend, and how I’m going to cope for a few months without a kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I have a chance, I may share some preliminary thoughts about those questions. For now, stay tuned.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 04 Oct 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145//kitchen145/finding-an-architect</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145//kitchen145/finding-an-architect</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Where We've Been</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Before I get into the details of what’s happening with the kitchen project now, I thought it would be a good idea to take a step back and explore how I got here. It’s been a long journey from deciding to take on this project to realizing it’s harder than I thought, and then having plans derailed by a once-in-a-lifetime public health crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was shopping for a place to buy, it quickly became clear that the kitchens fell into one of two camps. Either they hadn’t been touched for 30 years, or they were recently renovated, but with questionable taste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;images/shopping.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Questionable kitchen&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;One option I didn’t go for. The cabinet installers were so bad, I can tell some of the doors aren’t in alignment by looking at this photo, which is hiding many smaller sins. This apartment also had the disadvantage of being in a basement.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One apartment I looked at (sadly, I forgot to take a photo) had a kitchen that was more or less a corner of the living room in which they’d installed a $10,000 Sub-Zero refrigerator and a half-size dishwasher. Yes, I could have removed it after purchase, but then I’d have had to pay for a $10,000 refrigerator that I didn’t want. Others, like the one in the photo above, were clearly designed to tick boxes on a real estate listing, not work well as a system. One easy check: nothing I looked at had a dishwasher that cost more than my most expensive stock pot. Admittedly, my most expensive stock pot cost about $400 — which is a lot for a piece of cookware — but it’s also really not that much for a dishwasher. By comparison, that expanse of low-grade jet black granite probably cost upwards of $5,000. It truly boggles my mind someone would want such fancy worktops but skimp on way more useful choices, like spending the extra money to get drawers with nice runners instead of shelves in the lower cabinets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;images/shopping2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Questionable kitchen&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Another option I didn’t take. The second “bedroom” was more of a closet. Note that they did upgrade to (ugly) beige granite worktops to tick the “granite counter” box on real estate listings.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I chose to go for something that hadn’t been touched for 30 years. How hard could it be to scape together $20,000 to renovate a kitchen? As it turns out, pretty hard when you vastly underestimate all the leeches who siphon money off unsuspecting people when you buy a home and encounter some novel personal financial issues. (I’m not allowed to discuss those for legal reasons.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;images/current.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Kitchen&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A glimpse into my current tiny kitchen, taken the day I moved in.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time I had the money put together last fall, I also realized that $20,000 wasn’t going to be enough for my tiny kitchen and big ambitions. At the moment, I’m budgeting closer to $30,000, and I wouldn’t be surprised if I spend more like $40,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;images/sketch.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sketch&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The current layout.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this was a small project, the idea of hiring an architect seemed like an indulgence at first. I felt good enough planning something out with basic CAD software to hand off to what I hoped would be a competent contractor who might be capable of helping me iron out some of the more ambiguous details. My choices were fairly modest: Ikea cabinets to save money, locating services like plumbing to avoid expensive changes to the structure. Even that, however, proved to be too much. Every contractor I spoke to said I’d need an architect, if only to comply build local building regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;images/sketch2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sketch&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The renovation concept.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of, the process of finding a contractor isn’t one known for being pleasant. My experience didn’t do much to counter that. No one seems to have realized it’s easy to set up an email address, let alone a website. Hunting them down was a game of telephone tag. Call at off hours, and they’ve checked out for the day. Call during the day, and they barely give you notice because they’re trying to finish their work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I did find someone, it was not an especially productive relationship. Despite being a man, I’m pretty sure I fell victim to “mansplaining.” Because my kitchen was built in the 1950s, they decided to put the electrical panel in the kitchen. Rotating the layout virtually necessitates moving that, which is expensive, probably in the region of $3000. It’s a strange feeling to put that in an email and mention it on the phone up front, only to have the someone call and spend 20 minutes explaining it again, as if there was no way I could have understood it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, of course, the pandemic hit. With it came a construction ban in my building and the necessity that I work from home more or less indefinitely. The idea of living off microwave meals and takeout isn’t super appealing to me. But at least in the pre-covid world I would have been able to commandeer friends’ kitchens, eat out at restaurants, and travel freely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was the realization that the public health crisis may last for another year or more that pushed me to bring this project back to life. If I wait for the situation to really improve, it might be 2022 before I have a new kitchen — five years after I moved in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next time, I’ll share my experiences finding an architect to whip the project into shape. I figure, if I have to engage a firm anyway, I might as well have them help me build something that goes beyond my amateur efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145//kitchen145/where-weve-been</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145//kitchen145/where-weve-been</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Resurrection</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been almost three years since I bought my apartment with the idea of renovating the kitchen, and I still haven’t done anything beyond install a new dishwasher. The first hurdle was getting the money together. Even my tiny kitchen with modest upgrades is going to be fairy expensive. Then, of course, the world was hit with a pandemic. Stuck at home and without the ability to really travel or visit friends, I didn’t love the idea of living on a construction site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I realized we could be in this situation for a very long time, however. It’s time to take the leap and begin the renovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve set up this new blog to keep a running diary of the process. I’m hoping to keep interested people informed with a difference. Yes, I’ll have the usual photos and commentary of the process as it goes along. But I’m also going to be very honest about details that a lot of people seem to skim over. Living on a construction site isn’t fun, and major home renovations are not cheap. It’s misleading to imagine that you can achieve Architectural Digest-quality with pluck and elbow grease. I’ll spend more on my architects than you’d pay for a high-end watch or fancy handbag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m hoping that by chronicling all the little details most people omit, this will be a more interesting and a more useful guide for anyone else hoping to take on a project like mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my next post, I’ll piece together more of a project update recapping where I am today, and what’s happening as I dust off the project and get it moving again. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145//kitchen145/resurrection</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jkibe.github.io/kitchen145//kitchen145/resurrection</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>