<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Renovation Diary</title>
        <description>Joseph renovates his kitchen.</description>
        <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/</link>
        <atom:link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2022 07:52:16 -0500</pubDate>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2022 07:52:16 -0500</lastBuildDate>
        <generator>Jekyll v4.0.1</generator>
        
            <item>
                <title>Flooring Progress</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s all out of order, but I’m taking the progress. The contractor started installing the new flooring in a fuller way yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;flooring-low
flooring-interface
flooring-storage&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fire protection company made a visit on Wednesday. The sprinkler head definitely needs to be replaced: at the point it has any paint on it, it’s no longer useful. It will also be necessary to run a new sprinkler head in the new kitchen wall, so that the relocated cooking area is directly covered by a sprinkler. On the plus side, it should be possible to conceal the sprinkler in the wall, so I won’t have any weird pipe running across the ceiling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I’d like to hope otherwise, the person from the fire protection company suggested it could take many weeks just to get the permit to change the fire sprinkler, let alone actually do the work. All of which does not bode well from a time or cost perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/boxes-angle.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cabinets&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Another view of the cabinet boxes&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The millwork on the other side of the wall has started going in, though, which is good to see. It’s weird. The cabinet boxes are both smaller and larger than I had imagined now they’re roughly in place. I’m slightly worried about the space between some of the cabinets and some circulation space. In other places, it’s not as bad as I feared it might be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/flooring-start.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cabinets&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Another view of the cabinet boxes&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’ve also started putting down the new flooring. It’s really pleasing to see it in place, both from the perspective of seeing progress and knowing that I’ve made a choice I like for the new material. So much of this project is a leap of faith; it’s nice when the concept is just as good when executed as it is on paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot more of that to go. And the rest of the cabinets should go in soon as well. Those have been fabricated to custom sizes so that the limited space is maximized.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/flooring-progress</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/flooring-progress</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Millwork Begins</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;The bad news: it may take ages to deal with the fire sprinkler. The good news: work continues on the other side of the wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fire protection company made a visit on Wednesday. The sprinkler head definitely needs to be replaced: at the point it has any paint on it, it’s no longer useful. It will also be necessary to run a new sprinkler head in the new kitchen wall, so that the relocated cooking area is directly covered by a sprinkler. On the plus side, it should be possible to conceal the sprinkler in the wall, so I won’t have any weird pipe running across the ceiling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I’d like to hope otherwise, the person from the fire protection company suggested it could take many weeks just to get the permit to change the fire sprinkler, let alone actually do the work. All of which does not bode well from a time or cost perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/boxes-angle.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cabinets&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Another view of the cabinet boxes&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The millwork on the other side of the wall has started going in, though, which is good to see. It’s weird. The cabinet boxes are both smaller and larger than I had imagined now they’re roughly in place. I’m slightly worried about the space between some of the cabinets and some circulation space. In other places, it’s not as bad as I feared it might be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/flooring-start.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cabinets&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Another view of the cabinet boxes&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’ve also started putting down the new flooring. It’s really pleasing to see it in place, both from the perspective of seeing progress and knowing that I’ve made a choice I like for the new material. So much of this project is a leap of faith; it’s nice when the concept is just as good when executed as it is on paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot more of that to go. And the rest of the cabinets should go in soon as well. Those have been fabricated to custom sizes so that the limited space is maximized.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/millwork-begins</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/millwork-begins</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Moving Ahead</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;As it turned out, the project didn’t need to stop for the fire sprinkler. All that matters is having a sprinkler that meets requirements. Practically, that means some walls need to remain open in case the sprinkler does need to be adjusted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some isn’t all, though, so they were able to make some progress today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More specifically, they’ve started closing the walls on the kitchen side of the new partition. If I’m reading the materials correctly, they’ve used blue board rather than normal drywall. It’s made of the same stuff, but has a special outside surface designed to take veneer plaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/board-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Boarding on the kitchen side&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Closing on the kitchen side&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m guessing this is meant to help match with the existing walls, which are all plaster from the 1950s before gypsum wallboard became the standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fire protection company is coming on Wednesday to give closure (or at least what comes next) on the fire sprinkler situation. That should let the crew close the rest of the walls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, this should allow for the installation of the cabinets now that the kitchen side is closed up.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/moving-ahead</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/moving-ahead</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>It's Always Something</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Just when I thought things would start moving again, there has been another snag. In particular, there’s an inspection issue with the fire sprinkler in the former kitchen space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sprinkler itself has always confused me. In most buildings there are either sprinklers in every room or no sprinklers at all. My apartment — and all the others in my building, as far as I’m aware — have one sprinkler, and it’s only in the original kitchen spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On some level this makes sense. Cooking generates a lot of heat, and people often use oil to cook, which is another fire hazard. In a multi-family setting, I can see why it would make sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, it’s bizarre and frustrating. Most acutely, the lack of sprinklers everywhere means that I have to have a second means of egress from my apartment (beyond my front door), which is the reason I have a vestigial door in my bedroom that causes me no end of annoyances for no gain. Remedying that is a future renovation project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building inspection had two concerns with the sprinkler as the layout of my apartment has changed due to the renovation. First, that the coverage might not be as good or the same with the layout changes. Second, that the sprinkler might not work as designed because the previous owner did a shoddy paint job. The sprinkler isn’t supposed to be painted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The delay is annoying on its face. It’s even more frustrating because it has to be done by the company who manages the fire suppression systems for the entire building rather than the contractor. I have to do all the coordination myself, and I’m not optimistic the fire suppression firm will be especially prompt. See also the earlier asbestos incident. Moreover, there was a communications gap: I didn’t hear about this requirement for several days, adding some needless delay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until this is fixed, it’s effectively impossible for the contractor to make further progress on the actual construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There too it’s hard to stay sanguine. I finally got a revised schedule for the rest of the program. It puts the completion date in mid-September. That’s &lt;em&gt;two months&lt;/em&gt; after the original completion date on a project that was only meant to take three months. And the schedule has already been blown: according to the chart they sent, drywall was supposed to happen on Monday. That can’t possibly happen given the delay with the sprinkler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Framing inspection (25-28 July)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Insulation (28-29 July)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Insulation inspection (29 July-1 August)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drywall (1-3 August)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Base cabinet installation (3-5 August)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flooring installation (5-9 August)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wall cabinet installation (9-11 August)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Countertop templates (11-12 August)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Panel installation (12-17 August)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Baseboard (17-18 August)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Priming (18-19 August)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First coat (19-22 August)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Second coat (22-23 August)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Countertop installation (23-24 August)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cabinet handles (24-25 August)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Electric fixture installation (25-26 August)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plumbing fixture installation (26-29 August)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Punch list (29 August-5 September)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cleaning (5-6 September)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Final electrical inspection (6-8 September)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Final plumbing inspection (8-12 September)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Final inspection (12-14 September)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll make do — there’s not much choice at this point — but suffice to say cracks are beginning to show in my level of patience.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/its-always-something</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/its-always-something</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Inspected</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;There’s not too much to say for the last few weeks. But there was a bit of progress: earlier in the week the electrical inspector paid the site a visit, and passed the work. The project is still behind schedule, but this is encouraging progress to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a budget perspective, there were a few interesting twists. The plumbing work to move the sink and add laundry wound up being more expensive than the original scope of the project suggested. The plumber hadn’t anticipated needing to replace quite as much of the drain and vent stack from what I’m told.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the plus side, through some accounting I don’t totally understand, the very expensive extra plumbing work got offset with savings elsewhere, so only wound up costing about $1,000 more net.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking ahead, passing the rough inspections is a big step because it makes closing the walls (i.e., putting up the wallboard) possible. It goes without saying, that’s an important step in making progress.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jul 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/inspected</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/inspected</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Electric Progress</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;While I can’t quite tell if it’s done-done, there’s been encouraging progress on the electrical wiring. Most of the circuits are in place, and they’ve wired up my new panel to the original feeder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting to see all the circuits run. We think of electricity as being an almost magical force, but in reality there really is a run of metal wire all the way from the outlet to a power station somewhere many miles away. There’s so much wiring!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until the walls are closed and the outlets and switches are installed, they can’t wire up all the new circuits to the new panel. But, since I’m still living on site, they did make sure that the circuits in the living spaces have power, which resulted in the rather hilarious situation I’m in now with a single 15 amp breaker in the panel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/electric-rough-solitary.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Electrical panel&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;A solitary breaker&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the work is more straightforward. There’s a tangle of circuits by the sink for the garbage disposal, dishwasher, and the transformers required for the LED strip lights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/electric-rough-sink.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wiring near the sink&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;A tangle of circuits&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The circuits for the oven and cooktop are impressive to look at. Both appliances require more power — the cooktop I’ve selected can drive 7,700 W into a single pan! — which means they need an additional wire to get 240 V. They’re also much more substantial wires so they can safely run at 30 or 40 amps when they’re running at full power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/electric-rough-big.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wiring for the cooktop and oven&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;More substantial wiring for power-hungry cooking appliances&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not entirely sure what happens next. The inspection certificate on my front door suggests the electrical inspection hasn’t happened yet, and there are a couple of changes that need to happen on the electrical work so far. One outlet is in the wrong place. I’d also like to see if it’s possible to have a run of unconnected wiring left in the walls for a future bathroom renovation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/electric-progress</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/electric-progress</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Plumbing Progress</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Progress continues working toward completion of the first fix plumbing and electric. The plumber was on site several days running the new drain, water, and vent lines for the relocated kitchen sink. From what I can tell, everything is ready to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s kind of fun to see the parts of the old drain and vent stack that the plumber cut out to tie the new lines in. They’re very substantial chunks of pipe. Slightly more terrifying to peer into the old sections of pipe and see the accretion of sludge or corrosion or whatever builds up inside drain lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/plumbing-old-drain.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sections of pipe&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Drain and vent lines removed to make way for new adapters&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My building is about to spend $1.5 million replacing all the exterior balcony railings and floors. Perhaps the drain lines only need a good clean. I do slightly wonder how much it will cost and how complicated it will be if the drains actually need to be replaced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My inner software developer brain wonders why the building doesn’t require anyone who opens the wall to replace that section of drain and vent completely, or even subsidize that. Compared to the complication of opening and then reassembling the wall of everyone’s apartments in the future, the expense and minor complication of replacing the whole section seems negligible. Perhaps another casualty of the American delusion we can all be completely self-sufficient. Or our procedure fetish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I’m still waiting for the electrical question to be resolved, keeping my fingers crossed that they’ll let me get away with not having to run a new feeder wire. From what I understand, getting the electrical work done is the next big step.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/plumbing-progress</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/plumbing-progress</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Inching to the First Fix</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been an interesting few weeks. I spent over two of them elsewhere, mostly because I was afraid that as they got going on the more involved electrical and plumbing work, I might not have power or water. In the end, that didn’t happen, but it was still nice to escape the construction site and take a few days off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I was gone, a the project did make some progress. They removed asbestos, did more wiring, and (today) got going on the plumbing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the asbestos removal, they tore down what remained of the old kitchen wall, and then added new framing where that had been. From what I could tell, that was a relatively straightforward process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More involved (and still unresolved) was the electrical work. The most straightforward reading of the electrical code meant that I was initially required to upgrade my 60 A service — a relic from the 1950s — with 100 A service, the modern minimum. That requires upgrading the conductors that run from my apartment to the electric meter, no mean feat when that new feeder line had to run through a 70-year-old conduit buried in cast concrete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite several attempts, the electricians were unable to run the new feeder. The current plan is to go back to the city electrical department and argue that the actual load fits within the limits of 60 A service. It’s not a huge apartment after all. Whether that will land remains to be seen. I’m hoping it will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what I understand, the alternative would be incredibly expensive and disruptive: destroying the common hallway to run a new feeder through the ceiling there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/rough-panel.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Electrical panel&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The panel upgrade begins&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, more (successful) electrical wiring happened. Several new circuits were run, and they began the process of upgrading my panel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regulations dominated aesthetic considerations in one case. They had to add an outlet for the small run of counter space to the left of the new sink. The electrical code requires any run of counter space over 12” to have at least one outlet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/rough-kitchen-outlet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;An outlet&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;The wall paneling will have to be marred by an outlet&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More interestingly, they were able to wire for the LED strips using very narrow 18 gauge conductors, as (presumably) the LEDs are so low power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/rough-18.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;18 gauge&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Wiring for the LED strips&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work on the first fix plumbing also got started. There’s not a ton to see yet, only the beginnings of new drain and vent lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/sink-rough-drain.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;18 gauge&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;A drain for the new kitchen sink&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress, for sure. I’m less sure they’re going to make it to the early July deadline.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/inching-to-first-fix</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/inching-to-first-fix</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>The Pause</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Our strange economic moment strikes again. All other considerations aside, the biggest snag from the asbestos discovery has been time. In particular, a two week wait for the remediation firm to have a slot in their schedule to fit me in. So, I wait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s particularly maddening because this more or less has to happen before anything else can go on. From what I understand, the next steps are finishing the first fix plumbing and electric. The plumbing is literally blocked by the asbestos: it’s on the hot water lines. The electrical work is blocked by the incomplete demolition (blocked by the asbestos), and probably the workplace safety issues posed by discovering asbestos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what the firm said, they’ll be able to do the removal in a couple of weeks on the 6th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s nothing I can do about it, and certainly the asbestos should be removed. That doesn’t completely make up for the annoyance of another two weeks of living in the earliest stage of construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those interested in details, it’s going to run about $1,800 for the remediation work, plus $135 for the permit. Completion also requires that I engage an independent consultant to verify the environment is safe, another $350 to $500.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/the-pause</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/the-pause</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>The Hiccups</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with some good news. Since the last post, the flooring from &lt;a href=&quot;http://pidfloors.com&quot;&gt;PID&lt;/a&gt; arrived on site, as did the new ventilation hood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new hood is exciting for very mundane reasons. Namely, it’s really hard to get appliances right now. While there’s still quite a few to go — my oven probably won’t be here until August — progress is progress, and should be appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flooring is more of a relief. It was only ever possible for me to see photos of finished floors and a couple of small samples. That I still liked the choice when I plucked out a few full planks to look at was reassuring. I can’t wait to see it all installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/floor-plank.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The new flooring, up closer&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Real wood flooring to replace the Pergo&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now to the bad news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living in a well-established historical neighborhood has its benefits. Mature trees. Nice architecture. Streets designed for people, not cars. Unfortunately it also means old buildings with old building quirks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case, that turned out to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asbestos&quot;&gt;asbestos&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;images/asbestos.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Asbestos&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;If you've ever wondered what asbestos looks like, it's this&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a great insulator and fire retardant. It’s also a serious danger to human health, and has to be very delicately removed when it’s found. In my case, that’s around the main hot water line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From talking to the remediation company, the pipe insulation in my plumbing stack isn’t that big of a deal. They said it could probably be removed and certified in a single day. But it’s not going to be cheap. Among other things, I have to pay $350 just for the independent verification and certification after the material has been removed. People will be wearing serious respirators. Plastic wall barriers will be set up. And industrial-grade HEPA filters will be running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel like I really lucked out that I happen to have domestic-scale HEPA filters running as a matter of course and I have a vacuum cleaner with a HEPA filter I’ve been using to do extra cleanup. At least some asbestos has been disturbed as part of the work so far; it’s nice to know I’ve been protected. A very bare silver lining of the pandemic. I decided to buy them to assuage my guilt in having (a very small and select number of) people over during the height of pandemic in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other forces conspired to throw a wrench in one of the parts of my project I had been most excited about. It looks like I can’t have my in-unit laundry after all. Perhaps I should get a Costco membership and start buying breakfast cereal in bulk. I’m going to have a lot more closet space than I had anticipated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My contractor still hasn’t been able to provide a full schedule, so it’s hard to say exactly what comes next. Probably asbestos remediation, if I had to guess. That may also take care of the remaining demolition that needed to happen before the final framing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the framing is done and the asbestos is gone, my guess is that they’ll move to finish first fix plumbing and electric, including the high-stakes feeder wire replacement project.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/hiccups</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/kitchen145/hiccups</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>